<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../util/docbook/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
   xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <title>ANSI/NISO Z39.86-2011 Part B</title>
   <subtitle>Z39.86 Distribution Framework:  Primer</subtitle>
   <info>
      <releaseinfo>Public working draft</releaseinfo>
      <pubdate>21 May 2010</pubdate>
      <annotation xml:id="editors">
         <para>
            <personname>Daniel Weck</personname>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
            <email></email>
         </para>
         <para>
            <personname>Markus Gylling</personname>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
            <email>mgylling@daisy.org</email>
         </para>
         <para>
            <personname>Matt Garrish</personname>, <orgname>Invited Expert</orgname>
         </para>
      </annotation>
      <abstract>
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <para>The Z39.86-2011B Primer is a non-normative document that provides an
            introduction to the technologies and concepts behind the Z39.86-2011
            Distribution Framework.</para>
      </abstract>
   </info>
   <preface>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      
      <para>
         It is safe to say that DTBs have passed the phase of their existence where they can still be 
         called a new technology. DTBs are now ubiquitous, and the technologies they introduced, like the 
         Navigation Control for XML Applications (NCX), have been adopted into other standards,
         deeply entrenching the specification in the global publishing ecosystem.
         Even the original expansion "Digital Talking Book" no longer truly encapsulates the breadth of DTBs as
         an accessible format, but the acronym persists exactly because of the strong association
         that people now make between it and all forms of accessible publishing.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         There is always room to improve and always the need to evolve the DTB specification to keep up
         with the pace of technological change as the publishing industry moves more deeply into the digital
         world, however. To keep relevant and to ensure users are still receiving the best possible reading 
         experience, a new revision of the specification was undertaken by the DAISY Consortium. Some of 
         the key issues that this new version of the specification addresses are as follows:
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis>It brings greater distribution flexibility.</emphasis> The new specification allows multiple 
               versions of a DTB to be distributed in a single release, so users can choose which format type
               they prefer to read.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis>It brings greater production flexibility.</emphasis> The specification provides greater 
               format diversity, so readers and developers are no longer saddled with SMIL synchronization support 
               when they don't need or use it, for example.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis>It tightens the scope.</emphasis> The specification no longer
               tries to be every accessible output in one. Part A of the specification replaces DTBook as a means 
               of facilitating accessible text production and DTBs once again focus on their specific target audience.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis>It re-aligns the specification with standard technologies.</emphasis> Developers are
               no longer required to create custom components to process non-standard technologies, such
               as having to build custom browsers to display content. This change is expected both to simplify
               the creation of new accessible readers and to facilitate the playback of DTBs in mainstream readers.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
         The <link xlink:href="Z3986-2011B.html">Z39.86 Distribution Framework specification</link> is not the 
         optimal place to detail these and other changes
         that have been implemented, which is where this primer document comes it. This documents represents
         a simpler entry point into the technologies and concepts for readers who may be new to DTBs or who may 
         produce or distribute DTB content but do not require an intimate understanding of all the requirements 
         and restrictions outlined in the specification.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         The primer does not provide any new information that is not already in the specification, but endeavors
         to present the information in a way that anyone with an interest in DTBs will be able to follow and
         understand. References to the relevant sections in the specification have been included wherever possible.
      </para>
   </preface>
   
   <chapter xml:id="dtb">
      <title>What is a DTB?</title>
      
      <para> A DTB, stripped bare, is nothing more than a collection of electronic resources.
         When taken together, however, those resources allow a document to be rendered in 
         one or more ways conducive to persons unable to read traditional print media. The use 
         of the statement <emphasis>conducive to</emphasis> here is very much intentional, 
         as DTBs are intended to be useful to all digital readers, whatever their abilities.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Persons new to the accessibility field often arrive with the mistaken notion that a format 
         that assists one segment of the population with reading must by necessity come burdened 
         with aids and devices that would limit or exclude its use by another. Nothing could be farther
         from the truth when it comes to DTBs, however. If anything, the technology was ahead of 
         its time, providing a synchronized text and audio reading experience long before the audiobook 
         and eBook revolution that's taken off in mainstream publishing in the last few years.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         There are no limits on what type of document a DTB can represent &#8212; books, 
         magazines, articles from journals, a memo to employees, anything that can be written
         can be converted to a DTB.
      </para>
      
      <para> A DTB may be distributed as an audio-only publication (a structured "talking
         book"), a text-only document (e.g. an EPUB document), or it may blend features of
         both formats (synchronized text and audio). It may also layer video and SVG
         graphics, thereby enabling a richer multimedia experience. This new version of the
         specification also allows all of these formats to be combined and distributed in a
         single publication unit, allowing end users and/or reading systems to pick the most
         adequate consumption format. </para>
      
      <para> A DTB created in accordance with this standard makes possible a wide range of
         features: </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>rapid, flexible navigation (hierarchical or flat-listed);</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>synchronized playback (e.g. text and audio narration, text and video sign
               language, etc.);</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>bookmarking and highlighting;</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>keyword searching;</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>spelling of words on demand; and</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>user control over the presentation of selected items (e.g., footnotes,
               page numbers, etc.).</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para> Such features enable readers with visual and physical disabilities to access the
         information in DTBs flexibly and efficiently, and allow sighted users with learning
         or reading disabilities to receive the information through multiple senses. </para>
   </chapter>
   
   
   <chapter xml:id="dtbIntro_types">
      <title>What are the DTB types?</title>
      
      <para>Each type of DTB presented in this document offers unique characteristics
         dedicated to fulfilling specific operational requirements. However, there is also a
         degree of functional overlap. In order to avoid redundant normative prose in this
         specification, commonalities are described in independent sections that provide
         generalized definitions applying to more than one type of DTB. In some cases, the
         formal definition specific to a type of DTB may enforce particular restrictions to
         the rules inherited from the generalized definition.</para>
      
      <para>This specification details four types of DTBs:</para>
      
      <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>eBook</term>
            <listitem>
               <!-- <para> The eBook DTB represents a structured text document with rich
                  navigation and all the features provided by the EPUB format. </para>-->
               <para> The eBook DTB is defined in . </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Audio</term>
            <listitem>
               <!--<para> The Audio DTB represents a talking book and enables its most
                  basic manifestation: a play list of audio files supported by
                  mainstream playback devices. </para>-->
               <para> The Audio DTB is defined in . </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Classic</term>
            <listitem>
               <!--<para> The Classic DTB will be familiar to users acquainted with earlier
                  versions of the specification. It combines audio and text content,
                  using a simplified subset of the SMIL standard to ensure fine-grain
                  synchronization. </para>-->
               <para> The Classic DTB is defined in . </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Pro</term>
            <listitem>
               <!--<para> The Pro DTB adds support for the video media type and by doing so
                  provides a more complete multimedia reading experience to end-users,
                  covering a broad range of use-cases such as captioned and structured
                  movie clips, or synchronized sign-language and text books. </para>-->
               <para> The Pro DTB is defined in . </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter xml:id="dtbContents">
      <title>What's in a DTB?</title>
      
      <para> 
         Although DTBs are made up of many resources, not all DTBs will contain the same types of resources.
         It is true, for example, that every DTB provides navigation through the inclusion of an NCX file and contains 
         a package file listing its contents, but with four types of DTBs it may confusing to understand why
         other resources are included in some DTBs and not in others (even within a single DTB type).
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Following is a list of the various resources that you may encounter in a DTB, together with a description
         of their purpose and in which DTB types the are found:
      </para>
      
      <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Package file</term>
            <listitem>
               <para> The package file is an XML document that conforms to the Open
                  Packaging Format (OPF) specification and contains
                  administrative information about the DTB. </para>
               <para> The package file defines the DTB-level metadata, lists the resources
                  included in the package (the manifest) and defines the default reading
                  order of the document (the spine). For more information, refer to . </para>
               <para>You will find a package file in every compliant DTB.</para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Navigation control file</term>
            <listitem>
               <para>The DTB system supports global navigation &#8212; movement by structure 
                  (chapter, section, subsection) and by other selected points such as pages, figures, or
                  notes &#8212; through the Navigation Control file for XML applications (NCX) (refer to 
                  ... for more detailed information). </para>
               <para>You will find an NCX file in every compliant DTB.</para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term xml:id="overviewDTBContentSynchro">Synchronization files</term>
            <listitem>
               <para> To synchronize the different media files of a DTB during playback,
                  this standard specifies the use of the World Wide Web Consortium's (W3C)
                  Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL), SMIL 3.0 version.
                  The type of DTB determines the subset of SMIL features that are
                  available. Refer to ... for more
                  information. </para>
               <para>
                  SMIL synchronization is only found in the Classic and Pro DTB types.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Content files</term>
            <listitem>
               <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                     <term xml:id="overviewDTBContentText">Text data files</term>
                     <listitem>
                        <para> A DTB may include one or more documents containing the text data of
                           the document in (X)HTML5 format. The textual content file enables
                           properly-configured playback devices to spell words on demand, carry out
                           keyword searches, and permit finely-grained navigation. It can also be
                           accessed directly via refreshable Braille display, synthetic speech, or
                           screen-enlarging software. </para>
                     </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                     <term>Audio files</term>
                     <listitem>
                        <para> A DTB may include human or synthetic speech recordings of the
                           document embodied in audio files encoded in one of a specified group of
                           audio formats. Refer to ... for more
                           information about the allowed formats. </para>
                     </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                     <term>Image files</term>
                     <listitem>
                        <para> In addition to text and audio, DTBs may include images, <remark
                           role="todo">videos</remark> and other multimedia formats that can be
                           presented on players with visual displays. Refer to ... for more information about the allowed
                           formats. </para>
                     </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                     <term>Video files</term>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>
                           <remark role="todo">TODO</remark>
                        </para>
                     </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
               </variablelist>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Bookmark/highlight file</term>
            <listitem>
               <para> This standard supports user-set, exportable bookmarks and highlights
                  to which text and audio notes can be applied. The format of these files
                  is described in ... </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Resource file</term>
            <listitem>
               <para> The resource file contains or references various text segments, audio
                  clips, and/or images that provide alternative representations of
                  navigational information &#8212; for example, feedback on the user's
                  current location in the document. It supplies information normally
                  presented in a print book via typographical clues. </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Distribution information file</term>
            <listitem>
               <para> Given the typically large size of audio files, it is not uncommon for
                  DTBs to span several physical media units. <remark role="todo">add
                     link</remark> describes how the "distInfo" file maps the location of
                  each SMIL file to a specific media unit, e.g., disk 1 of 3. It also
                  explains how, when several books are distributed on the same media unit,
                  the distInfo file stores information about each book for presentation to
                  the reader. </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Presentation styles</term>
            <listitem>
               <para> A DTB may also include one or more stylesheets (e.g. CSS) to control
                  the presentation of text and image content in various media. </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
   </chapter>
   
</book>
