<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../util/docbook/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>ANSI/NISO Z39.86-2011 Part B</title>
    <subtitle>Z39.86 Distribution Framework Specification</subtitle>
    <info>
        <releaseinfo>Internal Working Draft</releaseinfo>
        <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
        <annotation xml:id="editors">
            <para>
                <personname>Markus Gylling</personname>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
            </para>
            <para>
                <personname>Daniel Weck</personname>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
            </para>
            <para>
                <personname>Matt Garrish</personname>, <orgname>Invited Expert</orgname>
            </para>
        </annotation>
        <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <para>The Z39.86 Distribution Framework (Z39.86-Dist) specifies the content and format for the distribution 
                of accessible multimedia publications. It defines four content types &#8212; an audio book
                format, an eBook format and both a light and rich multimedia format &#8212; each 
                targetted to the needs and requirements of persons who would otherwise not be able
                to access traditional print equivalents. The specification provides content producers with 
                the flexibility to tailor their content to meet the needs of their consumers, while at the 
                same time opening up the reading experience to a much broader range of individuals.
            </para>
        </abstract>
    </info>

    <chapter xml:id="introduction" conformance="informative">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <section xml:id="introductionAudience">
            <title>Audience</title>
            <para> This document is intended for organizations that create and distribute DAISY
                multimedia publications &#8212; commonly known as <link linkend="termDTB">DTBs</link>
                &#8212; and for implementors of <link linkend="termProductionSystem"
                    >Production Systems</link> and <link linkend="termReadingDevice">Reading
                    Devices</link>.</para>
            
            <para>
                Although knowledge of previous versions of this specification will be helpful in understanding
                the concepts and requirements outlined in this document, no prior knowledge is required 
                or expected. Knowledge of audio, video and image formats and XML schemas and markup
                is required, depending on the content type to be produced or device or system development
                anticipated.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="introductionDesignGoals">
            <title>Design goals</title>
            <para><remark role="todo">TODO</remark></para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="introductionOverview">
            <title>Overview</title>
            
            <para> The acronym 
                <link linkend="termDTB">DTB</link> (which originally stood for "Digital Talking Book") has outgrown
                its legacy as a replacement for analog audio books and in the process has become
                synonymous with accessible reading materials of all kinds. This specification 
                re-establishes and expands on the previous definition of a DTB to
                reflect this continuing shift. It provides new flexibility in terms of both the
                production and the consumption of multimedia publications, adapting and
                incorporating existing and new standards to enhance content, navigation and overall
                usability by visually-impaired persons and otherwise by people with learning or
                reading disabilities.</para>
            
            <para>
                Realizing that the size and scope of the specification may be intimidating as a result of its expanded
                nature, this section
                aims to provide a quick orientation to the concepts outlined in the document. The primary point 
                to bear in mind when starting to read this document is that it defines four unique DTB types, 
                and its layout is based on building on the information you will need to create or process any of 
                these types to minimize overlap and redundancy. As not all producers will be creating all DTB content types, 
                and not all developers will be targetting them, reading the entire specification from start to finish
                will consequently only be of interest to a small group of producers and developers. For the rest, the
                remainder of this section highlights key knowledge areas.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The specification then moves into defining the common functionality that is variously employed
                by the DTB types. Reading all of these sections, while useful, may not be necessary for many readers.
                Which sections to review depends on the DTB types you intend to create or process. It should also
                be noted that these sections cannot be read independently of the DTB definitions, as the definitions
                will, in many cases, introduce new requirements and/or supersede requirements.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                All readers will need to be familiar with the following sections, however:
            </para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <xref linkend="dtbLogicPackageFile"/>, which defines the package file that all DTBs must include;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <xref linkend="ncx"/>, which defines the NCX file format (the actual implementation of the NCX standard
                        is highly dependent on the type of DTB reproduced, so this section should always be read in conjunction
                        with a DTB definition); and
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <xref linkend="dtbDistroContainer"/>, which defines the container format for packaging all the DTB 
                        resources into a single file (use of the container format is optional, however).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <para>
                Which of the remaining sections in <xref linkend="dtbLogic"/>, <xref linkend="dtbContent"/> and
                <xref linkend="dtbDistro"/> to review depends on the type of DTB you intend to create or process:
            </para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        for audio books with no text, image or video content and
                        with simple playlist navigation, the Audio DTB format defined in <xref linkend="dtbAudio"/>
                        should be read in conjunction with <xref linkend="dtbContentAudio"/>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        for eBooks, with no synchronized
                        audio or video, the eBook DTB format defined in <xref linkend="dtbEbook"/> should
                        be read in conjunction with <remark role="todo">text definition link</remark>. Depending
                        on your eBook requirements, you may also need to review <xref linkend="dtbContentImages"/>
                        and <xref linkend="dtbContentVideo"/>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        for multimedia playback that allows the inclusion and synchronization of text and 
                        audio, the Classic and Pro DTB 
                        formats defined in <xref linkend="dtbClassic"/> and <xref linkend="dtbPro"/> should be 
                        read. Creation and processing of these formats will require knowledge of most of the sections
                        in <xref linkend="dtbLogic"/>, <xref linkend="dtbContent"/> and <xref linkend="dtbDistro"/>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="relationships">
            <title>Relationships to other specifications</title>

            <para>This standard is based on the specific versions of the standards and
                specifications referenced herein, which are used as defined except as noted by this
                document. Any refinement or replacement of a referenced specification by a newer or
                different version is not directly applicable to this standard. Conformance to this
                standard is based on the versions of the standards and specifications in effect at
                the time of publication.</para>

            <section xml:id="relationshipsZ39862010B">
                <title>Relationship to Z39.86-2011 Part A</title>
                <para> Z39.86-2011 Part A defines a framework for constructing XML grammars to
                    represent the structure and semantics of single-file documents. The goal of Part
                    A is to facilitate the transformation of text markup (including images) into a
                    wide variety of accessible formats, ideally including the text components
                    defined in this part of the specification. The ability to transform a Z39.86-AI
                    document into a format compatible with Part B of the specification is not a
                    requirement, however. </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="relationshipsZ39862005">
                <title>Relationship to Z39.86-2005</title>
                <para>Z39.86-2011 Part A and B jointly form a functional expansion of the <citation
                        linkend="refZ39862005">Z39.86-2005</citation> specification (otherwise known
                    as "DAISY 3"). Whereas Z39.86-2011 Part A supports the concept of a single file
                    dedicated to representing a "text" document, Z39.86-2011 Part B supports the
                    full fileset that defines a multimedia publication (externalized hierarchical
                    navigation and synchronization, packaging format, etc.)</para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="relationshipsXML">
                <title>Relationship to XML</title>
                <para>The document types defined by Z39.86-2011 Part A inherit all constraints
                    defined by <citation linkend="refXML">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0
                        (Fourth Edition)</citation>. Note that the later Fifth Edition of XML 1.0 is
                    intentionally not referenced here, due to a change in the XML specification that
                    relaxes Unicode restrictions on element and attribute names.</para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="relationshipsUnicode">
                <title>Unicode</title>
                <para>This specification inherits its relation to Unicode from <xref
                        linkend="refXML"/>.</para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="definitions">
            <title>Terms and definitions</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry xml:id="termDTB">
                    <term>DTB</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> DTB originally stands for "Digital Talking Book" (i.e. audio books),
                            but it is used in the context of this document to represent the wider
                            concept of DAISY accessible multimedia publications. A DTB is therefore
                            an abstract concept. Particular types of DTBs are formally described in
                            this specification, based on XML schemas, resource directories, and
                            normative prose.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry xml:id="termReadingDevice">
                    <term>Reading Device</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> The hardware/software platform that processes and renders the
                            contents of a <link linkend="termDTB">DTB</link>, for consumption by a
                            (human) reader. Sometimes also called "playback device", notably for
                            audio books. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry xml:id="termProductionSystem">
                    <term>Production System</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> The hardware/software platform that produces a <link
                                linkend="termDTB">DTB</link> fileset via human-driven authoring or
                            through automated transformations (or a chained workflow that comprises
                            a mix of the aforementioned content production methods).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>

        <xi:include href="./xinc/conformanceexpressions.xml" parse="xml"/>

    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbLogic">
        <title>DTB logic</title>
        <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile">
            <title>Package file</title>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_intro">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                
                <para>
                    The Open Packaging Format v. 2.0 (<xref linkend="refOPF"/>) specification defines the format for compliant
                    DTB package files. The package file is an XML file that contains administrative information about the DTB, the files that 
                    comprise it and how these files interrelate.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    The OPF specification represents a continuation of OEBPS v.1.2, which was previously used as the basis
                    for DTB package files. All implementers should familiarize themselves with the new standard, as this 
                    specification only provides an overview of the sections required to create conformant files.
                </para>
                
            </section>
            
            
            <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_impl">
                <title>Implementation</title>
                
                <para>
                    A package file is a valid XML document that conforms to the requirements outlined 
                    in the OPF specification (<xref linkend="refOPF"/>) and validates against the official 
                    schema  provided in  
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.idpf.org/2007/opf/opf2.0/download/#AppendixA">Appendix A</link>
                    of the specification. Some DTB definitions amend the requirements for compliance,
                    however, so please refer to each definition for additional requirements not outlined 
                    in this section.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    The package file should use the extension <code>.opf</code> to identify itself, but other
                    extensions are permitted. 
                    If a DTB spans multiple media units, the identical Package File must be present on each 
                    media unit.
                </para>
                
                <example>
                    <title>An example of a package file (informative)</title>
                    <remark role="todo">TODO: update to not be dtbook ref</remark>
                    <programlisting xml:space="preserve"><?example id='dist-package'?></programlisting>
                </example>
                
                <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_implRootIdentity">
                    <title>Package root and identity</title>
                    <para>
                        The <code>package</code> element must be the root element in all compliant 
                        package files. The <code>package</code> element must reference the OPF namespace 
                        <code>http://www.idpf.org/2007/opf</code> in its <code>xmlns</code> attribute
                        as well as declare support for version 2.0 in its <code>version</code> attribute.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        Each package file must also declare a package identity, a unique identifier for the 
                        publication as a whole. This identifier is contained in the <code>unique-identifier</code>
                        attribute on the root <code>package</code> element. It is not permitted to omit this
                        attribute or enter an empty value for it.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        The <code>unique-identifier</code> value is also used to identify the primary 
                        identifier for the DTB in the 
                        <link linkend="dtbLogicPackageFile_implMetadata">package metadata section</link>.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        The <code>package</code> element is itself made up of three required and one optional
                        section. The required elements, in the order in which they must appear, are:  
                        <code>metadata</code>, <code>manifest</code> and <code>spine</code>.
                        These elements may be followed by an optional <code>guide</code> element.
                        Note that the <code>tours</code> element has been deprecated and its use
                        is no longer permitted in DTBs. The requirements for each element are explained
                        in the following subsections.
                    </para>
                    
                </section>
                
                <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_implMetadata">
                    <title>Package metadata</title>
                    <para>
                        This metadata section of the package file typically provides publication metadata, 
                        such as the title, author and publisher of a document. It may also contain information
                        about the source document (publisher, copyright statement, edition, etc.).
                        All package files must include a single <code>metadata</code> element containing
                        this information.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        The <code>metadata</code> element must contain a single Dublin Core 
                        <code>identifier</code> element containing the primary identifier for the DTB.
                        This <code>identifier</code> element must have an <code>id</code>
                        attribute with the same value as the <code>unique-identifier</code> attribute
                        for the package (see <xref linkend="dtbLogicPackageFile_implRootIdentity"/>).
                    </para>
                    
                    <remark role="todo">Matt: detail metadata elements and usage per new rev. of the spec.</remark>
                    
                </section>
                
                <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_implManifest">
                    <title>Manifest</title>
                    <para> The manifest section provides a complete list of all the resources
                        (documents, images, style sheets, etc.) that make up the publication,
                        including the package file. </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        All compliant package files must include a single <code>manifest</code>
                        element as a child of the root <code>package</code> element. The 
                        <code>manifest</code> in turn consists of a list of one or more <code>item</code> 
                        elements, one for each resource in the DTB, that specify the location 
                        (<code>href</code> attribute) and the MIME type (<code>media-type</code> attribute)
                        of the resource in the DTB. The <code>href</code> values must be
                        valid URIs (<xref linkend="refRFC3986"/>) and the <code>media-type</code>
                        values must conform to <link linkend="refRFC2046">RFC 2046</link>.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        Each <code>item</code> must point to a unique resource in the DTB; fragment identifiers 
                        are not allowed in the resource URIs. Relative URIs are permitted and are 
                        resolved relative to the location of the package file.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        If a MIME media type is not available for a resource in the DTB, then an appropriate "x-" MIME 
                        media type must be used following the rules of  <link linkend="refRFC2046">RFC 2046</link>.
                        In the case of WAV files, the media type value <code>audio/x-wav</code> should be used.
                        This specification defines the following media types for file types defined in the specification:
                    </para>
                    
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>application/x-dtbncx+xml</term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>for identifying the NCX file;</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>application/x-dtbresource+xml</term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>for identifying the resource file.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    
                    <para>
                        The order of <code>item</code> elements within the manifest section is not significant, unlike in the 
                        <link linkend="dtbLogicPackageFile_implSpine">spine</link> where the order of resources references
                        defines the order of the DTB. There are two requirements for the identification of <code>item</code> 
                        elements, however: the NCX entry must include an <code>id</code> attribute with the value 
                        <code>ncx</code> and the resource file must have value <code>resource</code>. 
                    </para>
                    
                    <para> The distInfo file and any associated audio changeMsgs (or any other files
                        listed only in the distInfo file) are not considered part of the DTB and
                        are not listed in the manifest (see <remark role="todo">Matt: link needed if keeping</remark>).
                        The resource file and any associated media files must also be listed.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        A DTB may be packaged along with resources that represent an alternate rendition or 
                        that belong to another included DTB type (for example, a Pro DTB may be bundled with 
                        an Audio DTB). All such additional resources must only be listed in the manifest for the DTB to
                        which they belong. Two DTBs packaged together may have manifests that point
                        to the same resources, however (to shared audio files, for example).
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        The manifest may also include fallback declarations to allow players to choose 
                        among alternative presentation formats. Support for the fallback mechanism is 
                        not required by this specification, however.
                    </para>
                </section>
                
                <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_implSpine">
                    <title>Spine</title>
                    <para>
                        The <code>spine</code> element provides the linear reading order of the documents in the 
                        DTB. A compliant package file must include a single <code>spine</code> element after
                        the <code>manifest</code> element.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        The <code>spine</code> consists of a list of one or more <code>itemref</code> elements, each
                        of which must contain an <code>idref</code> attribute pointing to the id of an <code>item</code>
                        in the <code>manifest</code>. Restrictions on the type of resources that can be referenced in the
                        are specified per DTB definition (a DTB may only allow reference to SMIL elements or only to audio 
                        resources, for example). The restrictions outlined in section 2.3 of the OPF specification are superseded
                        by the individual DTB definitions.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        The <code>itemref</code>s must be listed in the order in which the resources are to be presented. 
                        A reading system must consult the spine when it reaches the end of one resource in order to determine 
                        which to render next.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        Primary and auxiliary content can be declared in the <code>spine</code> by the optional 
                        <code>linear</code> attribute. There is no requirement for a reading system to display this content
                        differently, however. References to auxiliary content should also be included in the 
                        <link linkend="ncx">NCX</link>.
                    </para>
                </section>
                
                <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_implGuide">
                    <title>Guide</title>
                    <para>
                        The <code>guide</code> element provides a set of references to fundamental structural 
                        features of the publication (such as the table of contents, foreword, bibliography, etc.),
                        simplifying access to them.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The inclusion of a <code>guide</code> element is optional and in most cases unnecessary,
                        as it provides functionality already covered in more detail by the NCX. Refer to the OPF
                        specification (<xref linkend="refOPF"/>) for more information.
                    </para>
                </section>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbLogicPackageFile_parent">
                <title>Activator(s)</title>
                
                <para>All DTB definitions enable the package file component.</para>
                
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbLogicSynchronization">
            <title>Synchronization</title>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbLogicSynchronization_intro">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <para>The DTB SMIL files define a sequence of media events. During each event, text
                    elements and corresponding audio clips as well as any additional visual elements are
                    presented simultaneously. DTB players use the synchronization information to both
                    access points in the audio presentation and to track, during audio playback, the
                    corresponding position in the textual content file.</para>
                <para><remark role="todo">TODO</remark></para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbContent">
        <title>DTB content</title>
        <section xml:id="dtbContentAudio">
            <title>Audio media</title>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentAudio_intro" conformance="informative">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <para> This section enumerates the audio encoding formats supported by a DTB.
                    Note that not all types of DTBs contain audio content, so this section only
                    applies to DTBs that effectively include audio data. </para>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentAudio_impl">
                <title>Requirements</title>

                <para> Reading systems must be capable of decoding at least one of the following
                    audio compression formats. Reading systems should be capable of decoding all of the following formats. </para>
                <para>Content must be delivered using one of the following formats, or may be
                encoded using a mix of the following formats. </para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>MPEG-1/2 Layer III (MP3) [<xref linkend="refMPEG"/>].</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Speex <remark role="todo">add reference link</remark></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>AMR-WB+ <remark role="todo">add reference link</remark></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                
                <para>Reading systems must ensure that playback of content encoded using a mix
                    different formats occurs without additional perceivable break in the playback
                    flow other than the noticeable change of audio quality (for example: difference
                    in bitrate). </para>
                <para> Reading systems must support mono audio formats (single channel).</para>
                <para> Reading systems must support rendering stereo audio formats (two channels) in
                    monoaural mode.</para>
                <para> Reading systems should support rendering stereo audio formats in binaural
                    mode.</para>
                <para> Reading systems may support multi-channel audio formats (more than two
                    channels).</para>
                <para> Content may include audio encoded with any number of channels.</para>
                <para>Content must not include audio encoded (at the file level) using variable
                    bitrate (VBR), audio must only be encoded using a constant bitrate for a given
                    file.</para>
                <para> Reading systems must support playback of audio at a depth of 16 bits per
                    sample, with sample rates of 44.1, 22.05, and 11.025 kHz.</para>
                <para> Content must use audio formats with sample rates of 44.1, 22.05, and 11.025
                    kHz (no other sample rate is allowed).</para>
         

                <para> Production Systems must support lossless uncompressed audio using raw PCM WAV
                    format (using single "fmt" and "data" subchunks) and may support other RIFF
                    media types. </para>

                <para>Reading systems may support audio encoded using WAV uncompressed PCM
                    format.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="dtbContentImages">
            <title>Image media</title>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentImages_intro" conformance="informative">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <para>
                    The image component enumerates the image formats that 
                    are supported by a DTB. The inclusion of this component in a DTB definition
                    requires that conforming DTB players must support the display of images.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentImages_impl">
                <title>Implementation</title>
                
                <para>
                    The inclusion of the image component permits the use of any of the following image formats 
                    in the creation of compliant DTBs:
                </para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Portable Network Graphics (<xref linkend="refPNG"/>), as expressed by the MIME type image/png</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>JPEG JFIF (<xref linkend="refJPEG"/>), as expressed by the MIME type image/jpeg</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                
                <para>
                    Although some formats may support animation, compliant DTBs must only include single-image graphics.
                    <remark role="todo">Matt: remove this if we don't add gif or a format that does support animation</remark>
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    The inclusion of the image component in a DTB definition does not include support for SVG images
                    by itself. Support for SVG is enabled separately through the <link linkend="featureSVG">SVG feature</link>.
                    The SVG feature cannot be activated if a DTB does not include the image component, however.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    The inclusion of the image component in a DTB definition does not
                    require that a conforming DTB include image resources.
                </para>
                
            </section>    
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentImages_parent">
                <title>Activator(s)</title>
                
                <para>The following DTB definitions enable the image component:</para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link linkend="dtbClassic">Classic DTB</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link linkend="dtbPro">Pro DTB</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link linkend="dtbEbook">eBook DTB</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentImages_ext">
                <title>Extensibility</title>
                
                <para>The image component can be extended by other features to include additional formats.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="dtbContentVideo">
            <title>Video media</title>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentVideo_intro" conformance="informative">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <para>
                    The video component enumerates the video types supported by a DTB. 
                    The inclusion of this component in a DTB definition
                    requires that conforming DTB players must support the playback of video content
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentVideo_impl">
                <title>Implementation</title>
                
                <para>
                    The inclusion of the video component permits the use of any of the following video formats 
                    in the creation of compliant DTBs:
                </para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ogg Theora (<xref linkend="refTHEORA"/>), as expressed by the MIME type video/ogg</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>MPEG1 (<xref linkend="refMPEG"/>), as expressed by the MIME type video/mpeg</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                
                <para>
                    Video formats not included in the above list are not permitted to be used.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Note that the inclusion of the video component in a DTB definition does not
                    require that a conforming DTB include video resources.
                </para>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentVideo_parent">
                <title>Activator(s)</title>
                
                <para>The following DTB definitions enable the video component:</para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link linkend="dtbClassic">Classic DTB</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link linkend="dtbPro">Pro DTB</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link linkend="dtbEbook">eBook DTB</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbContentVideo_ext">
                <title>Extensibility</title>
                
                <para>The video component is fixed and cannot be extended or modified by other features.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbDistro">
        <title>DTB distribution</title>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbDistroContainer">
            <title>Container</title>
            
            <section xml:id="container_intro" conformance="informative">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                
                <para>
                    The packaging of DTB resources is not a new issue, but is one that has not
                    been formally defined in previous versions of the specification. As a result,
                    producers have had the freedom to package their document sets in any of a variety of
                    formats as their needs required, while user agent developers have been left with the
                    problem of handling this variation when processing packaged DTBs.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    This specification seeks to redress this issue by formally defining the packaging
                    format and mime type for bundling the local resources in a DTB, as
                    well as to propose a common file extension format for the identification of
                    container files. This approach will allow the rapid deployment and exchange of
                    container files by removing the unnecessary ambiguity and investigation that has
                    existed regarding their format and structure.
                </para>
                
                <note>
                    <para>
                        Although remote resources are an integral part of a DTB, they are
                        referenced and obtained from their remote location by reading systems. Remote
                        resources can be obtained and included as local resources within the
                        container for distribution purposes, but any references to them in
                        the should be updated to point to their new local location to
                        prevent repeat requests by processing agents. </para>
                </note>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="container_format">
                <title>Format</title>
                <para> The DTB container format is a simplified version of the OEBPS Container
                    Format (<xref linkend="refOCF"/>) for bundling the various local resources that
                    constitute a DTB together into a single file. All the
                    requirements detailed in the OCF specification apply to the creation of DTB
                    container files, except where modified by this section. </para>
                
                <para> The DTB container format employs the modified version of the ZIP format
                    detailed in Section 4 of the OCF specification for packaging files. For identifying
                    that the file is a DTB container, however, the following MIME type must be
                    used instead: <code>application/z3986-dtb+zip</code> (see <xref
                        linkend="container_mediaTypes"/>). </para>
                
                <para> Each conformant container file must include a <code>META-INF</code> directory at
                    the root of the container as per Section 3.5 of the OCF specification. This
                    directory must include the required <code>container.xml</code> file detailed in
                    Section 3.5.1, which in turn must contain a <code>rootfile</code> element
                    that points to the DTB's <link linkend="dtbLogicPackageFile">package file</link>.
                </para>
                
                <para> The container may contain alternate renditions of a document, including alternate 
                    DTB playback formats, but must not contain more than a single document. </para>
                
                <para> The following conditions apply to the optional reserved files allowed by the OCF
                    specification: </para>
                
                <remark role="todo">Matt: any special conditions</remark>
                <!--
                    <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                    <code>metadata.xml</code>, <code>manifest.xml</code>
                    and<code>signatures.xml</code> are not a normative part of the Z39.86-AI
                    container format, but may be included if desired. Processing agent support
                    must not be expected for these files or for the signing of container files,
                    however. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                    <para> The contents of a Z39.86-AI container file must never be encrypted or
                    have digital rights management schemes applied to them, so the
                    <code>encryption.xml</code> and <code>rights.xml</code> files must never
                    be included. Where security is an issue, alternate means of protecting the
                    container file should be pursued instead. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                -->
                
                <para>The following is an example of the structure of a typical DTB container
                    file. </para>
                <remark role="todo">Matt: update with better example</remark>
                <example conformance="informative">
                    <title>DTB container file structure (informative)</title>
                    
                    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
mimetype
META-INF/
    container.xml
DTB/
    origin.opf
    On the Origin of Species.xml
resources/
    audio/
        origin1.mp3
        origin2.mp3
    images/
        darwin.png
    video/
        evolution.mpg
                    </programlisting>
                </example>
                
                <para> The <code>container.xml</code> file in the previous example would include the
                    following mark up pointing to the root DTB package file: </para>
                
                <example conformance="informative">
                    <title><code>container.xml</code> file mark up (informative)</title>
                    
                    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                        <![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<container version="1.0" xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:opendocument:xmlns:container">
  <rootfiles>
    <rootfile full-path="DTB/origin.opf" media-type="application/oebps-package+xml" />
  </rootfiles>
</container>
]]>
                    </programlisting>
                </example>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="container_extension">
                <title>File extension</title>
                <para> To facilitate the identification of the DTB container files, containers
                    should use the extension <code>.dtb</code>. Alternate file extension are permitted
                    so long as the container conforms with the ZIP requirements outlined in <xref
                        linkend="container_format"/>. </para>
                <para> File extensions are only a hint to the format of a container; the container's
                    <code>mimetype</code> file is the primary designator of the contents. </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="container_mediaTypes">
                <title>Media types</title>
                <para> This specification defines the following new media type: </para>
                
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><code>application/z3986-dtb+zip</code></term>
                        <listitem><para>identifies a DTB container.</para></listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                
                <para>Refer to <xref linkend="mediaTypeRegistration"/> for more information.</para>
            </section>
            
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbDistroAnno">
            <title>Annotations</title>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbDistroAnnoBookmark_intro">
                <title>Introduction</title>
                
                <para>
                    The annotations and bookmarks component enables readers to append notes to a DTB
                    and to utlilize bookmarking functionality to highlight passages of interest.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbDistroAnno_impl">
                <title>Implementation</title>
                
                <para>
                    <remark role="todo">Matt: lifted from 2005. needs rework or deletion depending on implementation</remark>
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    A reading system may allow readers to set bookmarks and to mark passages in a document, 
                    label the marked sections with text or audio notes, and export the resulting collection of marks 
                    and notes to other compliant playback devices. The inclusion of this component does not require
                    reading systems to support all of the functionality specified, however.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    This standard does not require that compliant players support all of the functionality described 
                    above. In addition, this standard places no constraints on a playback system's internal system 
                    for storing or manipulating the information in the bookmark file. However, if a player supports 
                    the export of bookmarks and highlights and their associated notes, the player must format the 
                    information as a valid XML file conforming to bookmark-2005-1.dtd.
                    Similarly, a player with bookmark/highlight import capabilities must correctly process bookmarks 
                    and highlights and their associated notes that are formatted in accordance with 
                    bookmark-2005-1.dtd.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Export-capable players must be able to set bookmarks and highlight starts and ends at any point 
                    in a DTB, whether based on the position in the audio presentation or the textual content file. That 
                    is, players shall not be limited to capturing location information only at element boundaries. Offsets 
                    from element boundaries in the audio presentation shall be identified by <code>timeOffset</code>,
                    with a clock value relative to the start of the SMIL time container referenced in the URI. The value 
                    syntax is defined by the SMIL 2.0 Timing and Synchronization Module [SMIL]. See section 7.7, 
                    "Media Clipping and Clock Values." Offsets from element boundaries in textual content files shall be 
                    identified by <code>charOffset</code>, measured in characters, counting from the start of the 
                    content of the referenced element; start- and end-tags are not counted, white space is then 
                    normalized (collapsed to one character).
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    If a playback device supports user-recording of audio notes on bookmarks or highlights that may be 
                    exported, the recording may be in any format supported by the standard. When generating the filename 
                    for a note, the playback device must generate a filename extension appropriate to the recording format. 
                    (See Section 5, "Audio File Formats" for supported formats and Section 3.3, "Manifest" for filename extension 
                    requirements.)
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Bookmark files (which may include highlights) shall be named, by default, with the value from the bookmark 
                    element uid and the extension ".bmk". For example: "se-tpb-14339.bmk". Players may allow users to apply 
                    their own filenames to accommodate character limitations in other filesystems and to avoid filename collisions. 
                    To accommodate user-supplied names, players with bookmark import capabilities must be able to open 
                    bookmark files and read the uid value to match the correct bookmark file with a DTB. It is recommended 
                    that if more than one bookmark file is present for a given DTB, players allow the user to choose among them.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Players may implement a variety of systems for numbering or otherwise identifying bookmarks or highlighted 
                    sections so the user can step through and choose from a group of them. However, when preparing a 
                    bookmark file for export, players must sort the bookmarks and highlights into document order and write 
                    them in that order.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbAudio">
        <title>The Audio DTB</title>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbAudio_intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            
            <para> The Audio <link linkend="termDTB">DTB</link> defines a type of audio book
                that enables flat (e.g. page-by-page, foot notes) or hierarchical (e.g.
                chapters, table of contents) navigation, whilst providing compatibility with
                mainstream playback devices thanks to packaging and architectural conventions
                such as the use of basic audio file playlists. </para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbAudioDef">
            <title>Definition</title>
            
            <para>
                The Audio DTB format supports only the functionality outlined in the following sections. If no
                reference is made to a particular functionality set, support must not be assumed.
            </para>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbAudioDef_audio">
                <title>Audio support</title>
                
                <para>
                    The Audio DTB fully supports the audio formats outlined in 
                    <xref linkend="dtbContentAudio"/>, as well as all requirements for their creation.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    It is recommended that Audio DTB content be created in MP3 format
                    for maximum compatibility with playback devices.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    It is recommended that audio content be split into structurally significant sections
                    (e.g., one file per chapter/section). Further, the naming of audio resources should
                    allow for the automatic ordering by name by reading systems that will not support
                    navigation by NCX or package file spine. To avoid the problems that arise with 
                    reading systems that use simple text filename sorting algorithms, padding of 
                    numeric identifiers on resource names so that they are equal length should be 
                    employed (e.g., starting with 01 if there are up to 99 audio resources in the DTB).
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbAudioDef_packageFile">
                <title>Package file support</title>
                
                <para>
                    The Audio DTB fully supports the package file format outlined in
                    <xref linkend="dtbLogicPackageFile"/>, as well as all requirements for their creation.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Unlike section 2.3 of the OPF specification (<xref linkend="refOPF"/>), 
                    the Audio DTB only supports references to audio resources in the <code>spine</code>.
                    The DTB may include resources in other formats in the <code>manifest</code>
                    where those resources serve a function other than as content (e.g. cover art).
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbAudioDef_ncx">
                <title>Navigation support</title>
                
                <para>
                    The Audio DTB supports the following subset of the NCX functionality outlined in 
                    <xref linkend="ncx"/>:
                </para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the root <code linkend="ncx.ncx">ncx</code> element must only contain child
                            <code linkend="ncx.target.list">target</code> elements;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the nesting of <code>target</code> elements is 
                            not permitted. Reading systems may create hierarchies from the list of targets to facilitate navigation
                            by readers, but it is not a requirement for conformance.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Each <code>target</code> must contain a text label consisting of one or
                            more characters (the <code>label</code> element is implied).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Each <code>target</code>'s <code>fragment</code> attribute must point to an audio resource
                            that complies with (see <xref linkend="dtbAudioDef_audio"/>).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                
                <para>
                    The normative schema definition for audio-only DTBs is available at
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.daisy.org/z3986/2011/ncx/">http://www.daisy.org/z3986/2011/auth/profiles/</link>.
                    <remark role="todo">Matt: add link to schema when available</remark>
                </para>
                
                <example conformance="informative">
                    <title>Sample Audio DTB NCX file (informative)</title>
                    <programlisting><?example id="dist-audio-ncx" ?></programlisting>
                </example>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="dtbAudioDef_container">
                <title>Container support</title>
                
                <para>
                    The Audio DTB allows the packaging of DTBs via the container format detailed in
                    <xref linkend="dtbDistroContainer"/>. Reading systems must be able to identify, unpack and
                    play resources so packaged.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbAudioFeatures">
            <title>Feature support</title>
            <remark role="todo">todo</remark>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbClassic">
        <title>The Classic DTB</title>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbClassic_intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <remark role="todo">TODO</remark>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbPro">
        <title>The Pro DTB</title>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbPro_intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <remark role="todo">TODO</remark>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="dtbEbook">
        <title>The eBook DTB</title>
        
        <remark role="todo">TODO - this is intended to be a reference to, or a
            specification infoset-compatible with EPUB 3.0</remark>
        
        <section xml:id="dtbEbook_intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <remark role="todo">TODO</remark>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter xml:id="features">
        <title>Features</title>
        
        <section xml:id="featureIntro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para><remark role="todo">TODO</remark></para>
        </section>
       
        <section xml:id="featureSVG">
            <title>SVG feature</title>
            <para><remark role="todo">TODO</remark></para>
        </section>
        
    </chapter>
        
    <appendix xml:id="ncx" conformance="normative">
        <title>Navigation Control for XML Applications (NCX)</title>

        <section xml:id="ncxIntro" conformance="informative">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            
            <para>
                The Navigation Control for XML Applications, commonly referred to as the NCX,
                exposes the hierarchical structure of a document to facilitate its navigation. The NCX is similar 
                to a table of contents in that it enables the reader to jump directly to any of the major 
                structural elements of the document (e.g., parts, chapters, sections, etc.). 
                The NCX typically contains more of the structure of a document than is included in a print 
                table of contents, however, and facilitates much finer-grained navigation, down
                to the page level in many instances.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The development of the NCX has been driven by the need to provide quick access 
                to the main structural elements of a document, especially in case where the complete
                resource may not be available before playback begins and/or would require expensive 
                parsing of the DOM to determine the structure (which in many cases might not render
                a usable hierarchy). 
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The format of the NCX was originally defined in an XML DTD included as part of the 
                Z39.86-2005 Specification for Talking Books (<xref linkend="refZ39862005"/>). 
                All DTBs and XML applications were required to fully implement the NCX standard in order
                to be compliant, which hindered the development of simple playback devices.
                In keeping with the profile approach to DTBs empployed in this specification, the NCX specification 
                has been modularized to allow different NCX profiles to be developed to more adequately and 
                efficiently address the specific needs of the new DTB types.
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="ncxNamespaceURI">
            <title>NCX namespace URI</title>
            
            <para xml:id="ncxNamespace" xreflabel="NCX namespace URI">The NCX namespace URI is
                <code>http://www.daisy.org/z3986/2005/ncx/</code>.</para>
            
            <para>This is the default namespace URI of all elements defined in the NCX modules.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="ncxModules">
            <title>NCX module and component definitions</title>
            
            <para>
                The following sections document each of the modules used to compose the various NCX profiles.
                This documentation indicates the default state and nature of each element prior to its activation
                in a module, so must not be read as a normative reference to creating a compliant NCX document.
                Each DTB definition provides a summary of the variations from the default states expressed here,
                as well as provides a link to the location of the normative schema that must be used for validation.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The documentation provided here has been extracted from documentation contained in each 
                of the NCX module files. In the case of any discrepancies between this documentation and the
                actual schema definitions, the latter shall be taken as authoritative.
            </para>
            
            <?absdef src="/mod/ncx-document.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/ncx-attrib.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/ncx-navmap.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/ncx-navlist.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/ncx-target.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/ncx-label.rng" ?>
            
        </section>

<!--            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementHead">
                <title>head</title>
                
                <para>
                    Contains metadata and other information about the NCX file.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementSmilCustomTest">
                <title>smilCustomTest</title>
                
                <para>
                    Duplicates customTest data found in SMIL files. Each unique customTest element that 
                    appears in one or more SMIL files and has been referenced at least once by a customTest 
                    attribute will have three of its attributes (id, override, and defaultState) duplicated in a 
                    smilCustomTest element in the NCX. The NCX thus gathers in one place all customTest 
                    elements used in the SMIL files, along with their defaultState setting, for presentation to 
                    the user. When a customTest element in SMIL has been applied to a time container holding 
                    one of the book structures defined in section 8.4.4 "smilCustomTest Element", the bookStruct 
                    attribute must be applied to the corresponding smilCustomTest and contain the appropriate 
                    value from the enumerated list.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementMeta">
                <title>meta</title>
                
                <para>
                    Each <code>meta</code> element contains metadata information applicable to the NCX file.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementDocTitle">
                <title>docTitle</title>
                
                <para>
                    The title of the document. The <code>docTitle</code> element may also allow optional audio, video 
                    and image renderings of the title.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementDocAuthor">
                <title>docAuthor</title>
                
                <para>
                    The author of the document. The <code>docAuthor</code> element may also allow optional audio, video 
                    and image renderings of the author.
                </para>
            </section>
            

            <section xml:id="ncx_elementNavPoint">
                <title>navPoint</title>
                
                <para>
                    The <code>navPoint</code> element represents a single navigational point within the 
                    <code>navMap</code> (i.e., a major structure within the DTB). It provides a description 
                    of the target content together with a pointer to its location. Depending on the type of
                    DTB, <code>navPoint</code> elements may be allowed to nest to represent the hierarchical
                    structure of a document.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementNavLabel">
                <title>navLabel</title>
                
                <para>
                    The <code>navLabel</code> element provides a brief, text description for its containing element.
                    The <code>navLabel</code> contains the section heading of the referenced section when 
                    used as the child of a <code>navPoint</code>. Multiple occurrences of the <code>navLabel</code>
                    element are typically allowed, for including labels in more than one language (the <code>xml:lang</code>
                    attribute must appear on each label to differentiate).
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementNavInfo">
                <title>navInfo</title>
                
                <para>
                    The <code>navInfo</code> element allows the producer of a DTB to attach informative information
                    and comments about a target location.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementContent">
                <title>content</title>
                
                <para>
                    The <code>content</code> element provides a pointer to the location of the content. The element 
                    may point to an entry in a SMIL file, where synchronization is necessary, or to a location directly 
                    in a resource. Refer to each DTB definition for more information.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementPageList">
                <title>pageList</title>
                
                <para>
                    The <code>pageList</code> element provides a listing of all the pages in a document,
                    facilitating page-by-page navigation and direct jumping to specific pages within documents.
                </para>
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="ncx_elementPageTarget">
                <title>pageTarget</title>
                
                <para>
                    The <code>pageTarget</code> element represents a single page location within a 
                    <code>pageList</code>.
                </para>
            </section>
            
-->

        <section xml:id="ncxConformance">
            <title>Conformance requirements</title>
            
            <para>
                Every compliant DTB must contain exactly one NCX document that validates to
                the normative NCX schema for the DTB type.  In order to be conformant, an NCX document
                must meet the following criteria:
            </para>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        It must be a well-formed XML Document as defined by <xref linkend="refXML"/>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        It must be namespace well-formed as defined by <xref linkend="refXMLNamespaces"/>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        It must constitute a single XML Infoset as defined in <xref linkend="refXMLInfoset"/>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The root <code linkend="ncx.ncx">ncx.ncx</code> element of the document must explicitly contain a 
                        <xref linkend="refXMLNamespaces"/> compliant  declaration for the NCX namespace, as defined in 
                        <xref linkend="ncxNamespaceURI"/>. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
        </section>
        
    </appendix>
    
    <appendix xml:id="mediaTypeRegistration" conformance="normative">
        <title>Media type registration</title>
        
        <section xml:id="mediaTypeRegistration_container">
            <title>DTB container format</title>
            
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Type name</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>application</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Subtype name</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> z3986-dtb+zip </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Required parameters</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Optional parameters</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Encoding considerations</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>DTB container files are binary files in ZIP format.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Security considerations</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> The file size and validity of container file data should always be
                            rigorously verified by processors. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Interoperability considerations</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Published specification</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> This media type registration is extracted from Appendix A of the
                            <link linkend="introduction">Z39.86 Distribution
                                Framework Specification</link>. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Applications which use this media type</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> There are no applications that currently recognize this media type.
                            This new type is being registered to enable operation within reading systems.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Additional information</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Magic number(s):</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> None. </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>File extension(s):</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        <code>.dtb</code>
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Macintosh file type code(s)</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>ZIP</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Intended usage</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>COMMON</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Restrictions on usage</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Person to contact for further information</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Name</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Markus Gylling</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Email</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>mgylling@daisy.org</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Author/Change controller</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> The Z39.86 Distribution Framework specification is maintained by the Z39.86
                                        Advisory Committee of the DAISY Consortium. </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        
    </appendix>

    <appendix xml:id="appendixChanges" conformance="informative">
        <title>Summary of changes</title>
        <para>The following is a summary of the changes introduced by this specification as compared
            to the previous version of the ANSI/NISO Z39.86 standard (<xref linkend="refZ39862005"
            />).</para>

        <section xml:id="appendixChangesOverarching">
            <title>Overarching changes</title>
            <remark role="todo">TODO</remark>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendixChangesNCX">
            <title>Changes to the NCX document type</title>
            <remark role="todo">TODO</remark>
        </section>

    </appendix>
    
    <appendix xml:id="acknowledgements" role="acknowledgements" conformance="informative">
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <para> The following are the members of the Z39.86-2011 Distribution Working Group
            responsible for the creation of this specification:
            <bibliolist>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Markus Gylling</personname>, <title>Lead</title>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Josh Altherr</personname>, <orgname>gh, LLC</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Douglas Blane</personname>, <orgname>Open University / Digital Audio Project</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>John Brugge</personname>, <orgname>Benetech</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Marisa DeMeglio</personname>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Wolfram Eberius</personname>, <orgname>Invited Expert</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Keith Fahlgren</personname>, <orgname>O'Reilly</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Reuben Firmin</personname>, <orgname>Benetech</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Geoff Freed</personname>, <orgname>WGBH</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Boris Goldowsky</personname>, <orgname>CAST, Inc.</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Sean Hayes</personname>, <orgname>Microsoft</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Ole Holst Andersen</personname>, <orgname>Nota</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Kenny Johar</personname>, <orgname>Vision Australia</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>George Kerscher</personname>, <orgname>DAISY</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Dominic Labb</personname>, <orgname>Humanware</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Patric Larsson</personname>, <orgname>SPSM (The National Agency for Special Needs Education and Schools, Sweden)</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Dennis Leas</personname>, <orgname>gh, LLC</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Bjrn Nyqvist</personname>, <orgname>SPSM (The National Agency for Special Needs Education and Schools, Sweden)</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Sam Ogami</personname>, <orgname>CSU</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Guillaume Olivrin</personname>, <orgname>Meraka</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Silvia Pfeiffer</personname>, <orgname>VQuence</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>James Pritchett</personname>, <orgname>RFB&amp;D</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Gregory J. Rosmaita</personname>, <orgname>Open Accessibility at the Linux Foundation</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Christian Wallin</personname>, <orgname>NOTA</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>Daniel Weck</personname>, <orgname>DAISY Consortium</orgname>
                </bibliomixed>
                <bibliomixed>
                    <personname>
                        <remark role="todo">TODO add all contributors</remark>
                    </personname>
                </bibliomixed>
            </bibliolist>
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The working group also extends its thanks to Michael Moodie and all the members of the 
            Z39.86-2005 working group.
        </para>
    </appendix>
    
    <bibliography>
        <title>References</title>
        
        <bibliodiv>
            <title>Normative</title>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refJPEG">
                <abbrev>JPEG</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.jpeg.org/public/jfif.pdf">JPEG JFIF V1.02</link>
                </title>
                <author><personname>Eric Hamilton</personname></author>
                <date>September 1, 1992</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refMPEG">
                <abbrev>MPEG</abbrev>
                <title>
                    ISO/IEC 11172-3:1993 - Information technology &#8212; Coding of moving pictures and associated 
                    audio for digital storage media at up to about 1,5 Mbit/s &#8212; Part 3: Audio
                </title>
                <date>1993</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refOCF">
                <abbrev>OCF</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://idpf.org/ocf/ocf1.0/download/ocf10.htm">OEBPS Container
                        Format (OCF) 1.0</link>
                </title>
                <date>11 September 2006</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refOPF">
                <abbrev>OPF</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.idpf.org/2007/opf/OPF_2.0_final_spec.html">Open Packaging Format (OPF) 2.0</link>
                </title>
                <date>11 September 2007</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refRelaxNG">
                <abbrev>RelaxNG</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c052348_ISO_IEC_19757-2_2008(E).zip"
                        >ISO/IEC 19757-2: Regular-grammar-based validation &#8212; RELAX NG</link>
                </title>
                <date>3 December 2001</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refRFC2046">
                <abbrev>RFC2046</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">Multipurpose Internet
                        Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types</link>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <personname>N. Freed, N. Borenstein</personname>
                </author>
                <date>November 1996</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refPNG">
                <abbrev>RFC2083</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2083.txt">Portable Network Graphics, Version 1.0</link>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <personname>T. Boutell, et. al.</personname>
                </author>
                <date>March 1997</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refRFC2119">
                <abbrev>RFC2119</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt">Key words for use in RFCs to
                        Indicate Requirement Levels (RFC2119)</link>
                </title>
                <date>March 1997</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refRFC3986">
                <abbrev>RFC3986</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt">Uniform Resource
                        Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</link>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <personname>Berners-Lee, et al</personname>
                </author>
                <date>January 2005</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refSMIL">
                <abbrev>SMIL</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL3/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL 3.0)</link>
                </title>
                <date>December 1, 2008</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refSVG">
                <abbrev>SVG</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-SVG-20010904/">Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.0 Specification</link>
                </title>
                <date>September 4, 2001</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refTHEORA">
                <abbrev>Theora</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.theora.org/doc/Theora.pdf">Theora Specification</link>
                </title>
                <date>August 5, 2009</date>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refXML">
                <abbrev>XML</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2006/REC-xml-20060816/">Extensible Markup
                        Language (XML) 1.0 (Fourth Edition)</link>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <personname>T. Bray, et al</personname>
                </author>
                <date>November 2008</date>
            </biblioentry>
            <biblioentry xml:id="refXMLID">
                <abbrev>XMLID</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/">xml:id Version 1.0</link>
                </title>
                <date>9 September 2005</date>
            </biblioentry>
            <biblioentry xml:id="refXMLInfoset">
                <abbrev>XMLInfoset</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/">XML Information Set (Second
                        Edition)</link>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <personname>J. Cowan, et al</personname>
                </author>
                <date>4 February 2004</date>
            </biblioentry>
            <biblioentry xml:id="refXMLNamespaces">
                <abbrev>XMLNAMES</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/">Namespaces in XML 1.0
                        (Second Edition)</link>
                </title>
                <date>16 August 2006</date>
            </biblioentry>
        </bibliodiv>
        
        <bibliodiv>
            <title>Informative</title>
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="refZ39862005">
                <abbrev>Z3986-2005</abbrev>
                <title>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/standards/resources/Z39-86-2005.html"
                        >ANSI/NISO Z39.86-2005: Specifications for the Digital Talking Book</link>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <personname>M. Moodie, et al.</personname>
                </author>
                <date>2005</date>
            </biblioentry>
        </bibliodiv>
    </bibliography>

    <appendix xml:id="TEMP_PLACEHOLDER">
        <title>TEMP PLACEHOLDER</title>
        <para>
            <remark role="todo">This is a temporary placeholder for IDs that dont
                resolve until the abstract definition is in place. If you see this in
                a built version of this doc, then something is wrong with the
                build.</remark>
        </para>
        <remark xml:id="ncx.ncx" />
        <remark xml:id="ncx.target.list" />
    </appendix>
    
</book>
