<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../util/docbook/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title><!--ANSI/-->NISO Z39.98-2012 — Core Modules</title>

    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para> The core modules are a set of modules that have been created to accompany the
                    <link xlink:href="../../z3998-2012.html">NISO Z39.98-2012: Authoring and Interchange
                    Framework for Adapative XML Publishing Specification</link> (Z39.98-AI). These modules serve both to define
                the common structure of a document and to provide a common base of components that
                can be drawn on for use across Z39.98-AI profiles. </para>
        </abstract>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <date>2012-12-19</date>
                <revdescription>
                    <para>Initial version.</para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </info>

    <chapter xml:id="intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <section xml:id="intro_overview">
            <title>Overview</title>

            <para> This document provides the definitions for the core modules developed to accompany
                the <link xlink:href="../../z3998-2012.html">Z39.98 Authoring and Interchange Framework for Adapative XML Publishing Specification</link>.
                These definitions are the human-readable descriptions that specify the nature of each module
                and component prior to their activation in any profile. Consequently, this document must not 
                be read as a reference on how to tag a document to conform to any specific Z39.98-AI profile, as 
                the actual implementation of a component in any given profile may vary from the definition
                given here.</para>

            <para> The <link xlink:href="../../z3998-2012.html#coreModules">Core Modules</link>
                section of the Z39.98-AI specification formally defines the purpose of these
                modules. In order to understand the definitions provided in this document and to be able
                to use them to build a profile, however, readers should also be familiar with the 
                <link xlink:href="../../z3998-2012.html#abstractDocumentModel">Abstract Document Model</link>
                and the process of activating modules, as detailed in the Z39.98-AI
                    specification. </para>

        </section>
        
        <section xml:id="intro_reading">
            <title>How to read this document</title>
            
            <section xml:id="intro_grouping">
                <title>Module groupings</title>
                
                <para> The core modules have been grouped according to the primary container layer in
                    the Abstract Document Model for the components they define. The first module listed
                    in each layer contains the default member for that layer, while the remaining
                    modules have been arranged alphabetically by name. </para>
                
                <para> In cases where a module contains multiple variants of an element, the module
                    appears in the first Abstract Document Model layer that contains the element (for
                    example, the <code>code</code> module is listed under the Block layer not the Phrase
                    layer, even though it contains variants for both layers). </para>
                
            </section>
            
            <section xml:id="intro_infoTables">
                <title>Information Tables</title>
                
                <para>
                    Each module and component definition includes a table summarizing pertinent information about it.
                    In the case of modules, these tables provide a quick glance at the elements, attributes, datatypes and/or
                    classes that they contribute. Module tables are only intended to provide an introduction to their components;
                    the information in the tables should never be relied on alone when constructing a profile.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Accompanying each component is a table that provides a detailed listing of its traits.
                    Depending on the type of component, the table may list the local name of the element, 
                    its namespace, its default usage context, its default content and attribute 
                    models and whether the component can
                    be altered and/or omitted during module activation. In the case of attributes, the content and
                    attribute model information is replaced by the attribute's datatype or allowed set of values.
                    More information about these traits can be found in the
                    <link xlink:href="../../z3998-2012.html#modulesComponents">Module Components</link>
                    section of the Z39.98-AI specification.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    The naming of columns in these tables may change depending on the nature of the component.
                    In some cases, a component's table may list its "Default Content Model" and in others it may
                    list a "Content Model" (and similar with attribute models, usage context and values). The difference
                    between a table item prefixed with the word "Default" and an item without relates to the 
                    alterability of that aspect of the component. If a content model can be altered on activation, for
                    example, it only provides a default content model (i.e., one you can use as is or modify to your
                    own needs). If the content model cannot be altered, then the listing in the table is fixed and 
                    must remain unchanged (the default modifier does not apply, as there is no other possible state). 
                </para>
                
            </section>
            
        </section>

        <section xml:id="intro_maintenance">
            <title>Maintenance</title>

            <para> The core modules are a product of the Z39.98-AI Working Group and are maintained
                and hosted by the Z39.98 Advisory Committee.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="intro_versioning">
            <title>Changes to this document</title>

            <para> This document is not subject to the same update process as the Z39.98-AI
                specification. It may be updated at any time to add new modules or to change or
                deprecate modules and components. The publication date and revision history of this
                document should always be checked to ensure the latest version is being referenced.
                The current official version of this document is available from the DAISY web site
                at <link xlink:href="http://www.daisy.org/z3998/2012/auth/cm/"
                    >http://www.daisy.org/z3998/2012/auth/cm/</link>. </para>

        </section>

    </chapter>

    <chapter xml:id="coreModuleDefinitions">
        <title>Module and component definitions</title>

            <para> The definitions contained in this section have been extracted from the
                module and component metadata in the corresponding normative schema files. In the
                case of discrepancies between the prose abstract definitions and the practical
                definition of components in the normative schemas, the latter shall be taken as
                authoritative. </para>
        

        <!-- note: the URIs of @src in absdef is relative to schema root dir, 
        not relative to this document -->

        <section xml:id="absdef_document">
            <title>Document foundation</title>
            <para> The document foundation modules define the common base of all profiles. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-document.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-datatypes.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-global-classes.rng" ?>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="absdef_section">
            <title>Section layer</title>
            <para> The Section layer modules define major structural components for use within
                documents. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-section.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-article.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-bibliography.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-cover.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-glossary.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-index.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-partitions.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-toc.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-verse.rng" ?>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="absdef_block">
            <title>Block layer</title>
            <para> The Block layer modules define components that are not structural in nature but
                that can stand alone from their surroundings. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-block.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-address.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-annotation.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-aside.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-byline.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-caption.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-citation.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-code.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-dateline.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-definition.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-description.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-headings.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-list.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-meta.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-note.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-object.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-p.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-pagebreak.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-quote.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-transition.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-table.rng" ?>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="absdef_phrase">
            <title>Phrase layer</title>
            <para> The Phrase layer modules define constructs that operate at the grammatical level. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-span.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-abbr.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-d.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-emph.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-line.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-linking.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-name.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-num.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-s.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-term.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-time.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-w.rng" ?>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="absdef_text">
            <title>Text layer</title>
            <para> The Text layer modules define character data and elements whose semantics operate
                at a character level. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-sub-sup.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-char.rng" ?>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="absdef_globalAttributes">
            <title>Global attributes</title>
            <para> The Global attributes modules define attributes that are available across the
                elements in a profile. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-by-attrib.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-core-attrib.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-depth-attrib.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-i18n-attrib.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/xlink.rng" ?>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="absdef_metaAttributes">
            <title>Metadata attributes</title>
            <para> The Metadata attributes modules define attributes that allow meta information and
                semantics to be appended to elements in a profile. </para>
            <?absdef src="/mod/rdfa-attrib.rng" ?>
            <?absdef src="/mod/z3998-role-attrib.rng" ?>
        </section>

    </chapter>


</book>
