<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../RelaxNG/daisy-leisure-profile-driver.rng" type="xml"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2002/06/xhtml2/" xmlns:d="http://www.daisy.org/ns/z3986/2008/"
   xml:lang="en">
   <head>
      <title>The Project Gutenberg eBook of Rosa's Quest, by Anna Potter Wright</title>
      <meta property="title">The Project Gutenberg eBook of Rosa's Quest, by Anna Potter
         Wright</meta>
   </head>
   <d:book>
      <d:frontmatter>
         <section>
            <h>Rosa's Quest, The Way to the Beautiful Land</h>
            <p>The Project Gutenberg eBook, Rosa's Quest, by Anna Potter Wright</p>
            <p>Title: Rosa's Quest The Way to the Beautiful Land</p>
            <p>Author: Anna Potter Wright</p>
            <p>Release Date: November 25, 2005 [eBook #17152]</p>
            <p>Language: English</p>
            <p>E-text prepared by Marilynda Fraser-Cunliffe, Josephine Paolucci, and the Project
               Gutenberg Online Distributed Proofreading Team (http://www.pgdp.net/) </p>
         </section>
      </d:frontmatter>
      <d:bodymatter>
         <section>
            <h>I. "HOW MUCH IS THE FARE?"</h>
            <p>"Rosa! Rosa!"</p>
            <p>"Yes'm, Mis' Gray, I'm coming."</p>
            <p>"Well, fer land sakes then, hurry up, you lazy girl! I've been a-hollerin' till my
               throat's sore. You're always underfoot when you ain't wanted, then when you are
               wanted, you're no place to be found. If you wuz my girl, you'd be learnt to know
               more'n you know now, I can tell you that. I believe in young uns amountin' to
               somethin', but it's mighty little you know." </p>
            <p>"But, Mis' Gray," faltered poor little Rosa, "mother was coughing awful, and I didn't
               hear you." </p>
            <p>"Yes, your ma ag'in. I don't know what you'll have fer an excuse when she's gone, or
               what'll become of you either. I know one thing, though; I won't have you. But it'd be
               a heap sight better fer you if I would, and a real blessin', too." </p>
            <p>"Why, where's mother going, Mis' Gray?" asked Rosa with wide-open and frightened
               eyes. </p>
            <p>"There, there, Sary, don't talk to the child so! Never mind, Rosa dear, Sary don't
               mean it. Sary's a good woman, yes, a very good woman." </p>
            <p>"I do too mean it, father, and I jest want you to keep still. You always take her
               part. Yes, I am a good woman, or I'd never kep' you after poor Tom got killed. I have
               to sew my finger ends off to git us enough to eat and to pay the rent. I always did
               have bad luck from the day I married Tom Gray. He would insist on keepin' you, and
               you wuz sick that summer he couldn't git no work. He'd walk all day a-tryin' to find
               somethin' to do, then set up all night with you, though I told him it wuzn't
               necessary. I washed and I sewed and I done everything, but our little home had to go.
               I thought then, and I think now, that we could a-kep' it, if it hadn't been fer you.
               If Tom could git hold of a cent at all, it would go fer medicine, or somethin' fer
               you to eat. After you got well, he found a place to work, and wuz a-tryin' to git
               back the home, when he went and got killed, a-tryin' to keep a poor, good-fer-nothin'
               beggar from bein' run over by the streetcar. All he left me wuz you to look after,
               and you ain't never had a bit of sense, since the day he wuz brought home to me all
               torn and bleedin'. There ain't many that's had as much to put up with as I have. I
               guess most daughters-in-law would jest have told you to leave, but no, I've been
               a-keepin' you fer the last five years, and no tellin' how much longer you'll live!
               And you didn't mind me this mornin', and I sprained my ankle a-goin'—" </p>
            <p>"Grandpa," broke in Rosa, heedless of Mrs. Gray's irascible tongue, "what does she
               mean about mother going away?" </p>
            <p>"Why, I don't know, child; I ain't heard no talk about her leavin', but then I git
               things so mixed up since Tom died." </p>
            <p>"Rosa Browning, I didn't call you in here to ask foolish questions. I want you to
               deliver this package, and quick, too. If you hadn't talked so much, you could be well
               on your way by this time. It goes to that lady over on Lake Avenue, where I sent you
               once before." </p>
            <p>"Oh, where I heard the beautiful music?"</p>
            <p>"Yes, but don't you loiter on your way to listen to no music! Fine music ain't for
               the likes of us here on Burton street. It's a shame fer me to have to pay your
               carfare, but I 'spose you can't carry that big package so far. If you'd spend a
               little more time a-workin', and a little less a-lookin' after your ma, you'd have
               more strength, I won't have it said that I git work done fer nothin', so I'll give
               you ten cents besides. You git a piece of beefsteak with it, and I'll broil it fer
               your ma's supper. You couldn't fix it fit to eat, nohow. I hope to goodness she won't
               cough all night and keep me awake." </p>
            <p>"Oh, thank you, Mis' Gray, you are so kind," delightedly exclaimed Rosa, her wan
               little face lighting up with genuine pleasure at the thought that mother was going to
               have something good for supper. </p>
            <p>"Now do be gone, and don't talk no more. You're enough to set me crazy, you and
               father." </p>
            <p>"I'm off now, Mis' Gray. Goodby, grandpa dear," she affectionately said, kissing the
               old man's withered cheek, for these two children of the tenement, the one eight and
               the other eighty, were the best of friends. </p>
            <p>"Rosa," called once again Mrs. Gray's shrill voice, as the child was making her way
               across the dark hall, "come back here!" </p>
            <p>"Yes'm, Mis' Gray, here I am."</p>
            <p>"You're so awful careless, you see to it that you don't lose that money I give you.
               If you do, you'll be sorry. You won't git the pay fer the work; I wouldn't trust you
               with that, nohow. Now hurry up and don't waste another minute! Wait! can't you
                  <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="10" />give me a chance to tell
               you what I want? You're so provokin'. Be sure to tell your ma where you're goin', and
               that it'll take you about an hour and a half. I don't want her a-gettin' scared and
               a-hollerin' 'round and a-sendin' some one after you, like she did that day you didn't
               git home till dark. She acted ridiculous, as if she thought you never would come
               back. I couldn't fer the life of me see what made her do so; it was real silly, and I
               told her so at the time. I did think, though, that you'd ought to be licked fer not
               hurryin' up more, but she jest kissed you and cried all the more when I said so. Go
               and tell her now, and be sure you don't drop that package in the dirt." </p>
            <p>This time Rosa started on a run, lest she might be called back once more. She feared
               the tyrant, but vainly endeavored to love her for grandpa's sake. He so often told
               her that "Sary was a good woman, yes, a very good woman." </p>
            <p>"Mother dear," she said, upon entering their one poverty-stricken, but scrupulously
               neat, little room, "I'm going to deliver a package over on Lake Avenue for Mis' Gray,
               and will not be back for about an hour and a half, she told me to tell you; and she
               gave me ten cents, too. Ain't that nice? I'm going to get some beefsteak, and she'll
               broil it. </p>
            <p>"But, mother, she said something about your going <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="11" />away, and didn't know what would become
               of me. You won't move, will you, without taking me along? I don't know what she could
               have meant. What did she mean, anyhow? Why do you cry, mother dear?" tremulously
               inquired the child, rushing impulsively up to the side of the bed. </p>
            <p>"We'll talk when you come back, darling. Kiss me, my precious"; and the sufferer fell
               back upon her pillow, coughing violently, and moaning for very agony of spirit. </p>
            <p>With a heart heavier than the huge package, Rosa sped down the steep stairway, out
               into the bitter December weather. </p>
            <p>"Oh," she said, half audibly, "how cold it is! I'm glad I haven't far to go to take
               the car." </p>
            <p>Quickly her nimble feet carried her, and in a few minutes she was scrutinizing the
               faces of her fellow-passengers. Sitting across the aisle from her was a young lady,
               who to Rosa seemed the embodiment of beauty and elegance. While intently studying the
               fair face and neat costume, this object of her admiration suddenly crossed the car
               and sat down by her side. The sweet smile and cordial greeting made the child forget
               her timidity, and soon the two were conversing most familiarly. </p>
            <p>"And so you are going to deliver that package over on Lake Avenue, are you?" </p>
            <p>"Yes'm, and Mis' Gray gave me ten cents fer it, too. I'm going to get some steak, and
               she will broil it for mother's supper. Ain't that nice? I'd think I'd be happy, but I
               ain't a bit. I keep wondering what she meant about mother going away, and she didn't
               know what would become of me. Why, lady, mother just can't move now; she's sick and
               has a dreadful cough! She hasn't even been in to see grandpa and Mis' Gray for a long
               time. Then I know, anyhow, she'd never go and leave me. Of course she wouldn't, for
               we're always together. She couldn't get along without me, 'cause I take care of her,
               and I know I couldn't get along without her at all. Mis' Gray ought to know that, for
               we've lived by her a long time. What do you 'spose she meant? I can't think about
               anything else." </p>
            <p>"Why, my little girl," replied the stranger, while Rosa was more mystified than ever
               to see the blue eyes fill with tears, "sometimes when people are sick, they go to a
               better country than this. Do you know about heaven?" </p>
            <p>"Not much, ma'am. When Mis' Gray goes away and mother's working, grandpa gets his old
               violin and sings to me about the beautiful land. He says that's heaven, but he can't
               explain it much to me. He says he can't think right since Tom got killed. You know
                  <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="13" /> Tom was his boy. Grandpa is
               so good. When mother moves, I know she will take me, and I wish he could go too. But,
               lady, do you 'spose that's the place where mother's going?" </p>
            <p>"I hope so, dear, for she would not cough any more there."</p>
            <p>"Oh, wouldn't she? I'll tell her about it, then. But how much is the fare? We're
               poor, you know." </p>
            <p>"You do not have to pay any fare to go to that beautiful land, because Jesus paid it
               all long ago." </p>
            <p>"Oh, how kind! He must be so good. Last night I wakened, and mother kissed me and
               said that Jesus surely would take care of me. Are you real sure He paid the fare for
               everybody?" </p>
            <p>"Yes, I know it, for God so loved the world that He gave His only begotten Son, that
               whosoever believeth in Him should not perish, but have everlasting life." </p>
            <p>"Ain't that pretty! But where do you start from to get there?"</p>
            <p>"Your mother could go right from your home."</p>
            <p>"But she just ain't able to go any place; she can't sit up much now. I'll tell her
               about it, though, then when she's better, we'll both go. Does it take long to get
               there?" </p>
            <p>"No, not so very."</p>
            <p>"I wish we'd known it before it got so cold. It <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="14" />might make her cough worse to go out now.
               Are there many people in this land?" </p>
            <p>"Yes, a great many."</p>
            <p>"Are there more going?"</p>
            <p>"Yes, they are going all the time."</p>
            <p>"Do people here in the city know about it?"</p>
            <p>"Yes."</p>
            <p>"Then why didn't somebody tell me before mother got so sick? I just can't bear to see
               her suffer so, and we might be there now. I'm afraid it will be a long time before
               she's well enough to start. Oh, if I'd only known! I'd think somebody should have
               told me. </p>
            <p>"Do folks have enough to eat there? Sometimes since mother's not been able to work
               much, we get so awful hungry." </p>
            <p>"They have everything they want, and never get hungry."</p>
            <p>"Everything they want, and never get hungry?"</p>
            <p>"Yes."</p>
            <p>"And is it cold there?"</p>
            <p>"No."</p>
            <p>"Do they have to pay rent?"</p>
            <p>"No, for Jesus has paid for everything."</p>
            <p>"Oh, oh! won't it be nice? How glad mother will be when I tell her, for it has been
               so hard for us to <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="15" />get along
               this winter. The rent is due next Monday, and we have nothing to pay it with, but if
               mother is just well enough to go, it won't make no difference. But the very best part
               of all, she won't be coughing any more! </p>
            <p>"Oh!" half screamed Rosa, "I forgot to get off, and have gone a whole block past Lake
               Avenue. What would Mis' Gray say to me?" </p>
            <p>Without another word she was gone, for already the car was beginning to move on.
               Scarcely realizing what she did, she ran after it for a short distance. With a great
               pang, she remembered that the girl had not told her the way to the beautiful land,
               where mother might go and never cough any more. </p>
            <p>Half stunned by bewilderment and disappointment, and with her heart heavier than
               before, she delivered her package, purchased the steak, and in due time was again at
               the sufferer's bedside. </p>

            <!-- End of level2-->
         </section>
         <section>
            <h>II. ESTHER'S PERPLEXITY.</h>
            <p>The day was gradually fading into darkness.</p>
            <p>Esther Fairfax, with sadness upon her usually sunshiny face, was sitting before her
               cheery open fire, fruitlessly endeavoring to become interested in her newly-purchased
               book. </p>
            <p>Her room was by no means elegantly furnished, but every article it contained, from
               the rugs upon the floor to the pictures upon the wall, reflected the refinement and
               culture of the fair young occupant. </p>
            <p>Presently, closing her book and tossing it carelessly from her hand, she settled back
               upon her couch for good solid meditation, while tears gathered in her deep blue eyes,
               chasing each other in rapid succession down her flushed cheeks. </p>
            <p>For some time she lived over the events of the afternoon, recalling minutely the
               details of the unusual conversation with the untaught but interesting child. </p>
            <p>"Oh," she thought, "I shall never forget those words, 'How much is the fare? We're
               poor you know.' If only I knew where she lives, that I might go and see her and
               minister to the comforts of the dying mother! The hungry wistfulness of those eyes
               seems burned into my very soul. </p>
            <p>"Father, I am so glad you have come," she said, hastily rising upon hearing the
               familiar footstep in the hall. "I have been waiting a long time for your return." </p>
            <p>"Why, my child, you have been crying. What is it? Are you ill, or have you received
               an unwelcome message?" </p>
            <p>"No, neither, father, but I am so troubled about a little girl I saw in the car this
               afternoon, and who disappeared almost magically." </p>
            <p>"Come into my study and tell me all about it, Esther."</p>
            <p>Although Dr. Fairfax was the pastor of one of the largest churches in the city, he
               always had time for his beloved and motherless daughter. </p>
            <p>"When I was coming from down town this afternoon," she began, "a very small girl with
               a very large <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="18" />package in her
               arms stepped aboard the car. Her face was so sweet and innocent that one would notice
               it even in a crowd, but overshadowed by an expression of care far too heavy for her
               baby years. Her eyes were large, dark and unusually lustrous, while her wavy brown
               hair fell about her face and neck in rich profusion. Her clothing was scant and old,
               but clean and very neatly mended. The whole appearance of the child was so
               pathetically irresistible that I went and sat down by her side, taking her cold
               little hand within my own. </p>
            <p>"She talked freely, telling me that her name is Rosa Browning. As I now recall the
               conversation, I find that I know but little indeed of her actual circumstances, and
               nothing at all of the location of her home. </p>
            <p>"She spoke most tenderly now and then of 'grandpa', and occasionally mentioned 'Mis'
               Gray', who, I imagine, is not specially noted for her amiability. But oh, father,
               when she would refer to her mother, it seemed that her heart was almost crushed with
               anxiety, and that her burden was greater than she could bear!" </p>
            <p>With tears still flowing, Esther then told of Rosa's bewilderment concerning her
               mother's rumored moving, and of her own efforts to explain what this moving probably
               meant. </p>
            <p>The strong man, accustomed as he was to the tales <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="19" />of woe and misery among the poor and
               outcast, bowed his head and wept also. The pathos of the child's simple, direct
               questions impressed him quite as much as it had Esther. </p>
            <p>"'But how much is the fare? How much is the fare?'" he repeated over and over. </p>
            <p>"Truly you answered well, daughter. We have no fare to pay, no, none, for Jesus paid
               it all! But what a price—the life of the Son of the Most High God, who, being in the
               form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God: but made Himself of no
               reputation, and took upon Him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of
               men: and being found in fashion as a man, He humbled Himself, and became obedient
               unto death, even the death of the cross!" </p>
            <p>For some minutes they remained in silence, lost in the thought of the price of
               redemption. </p>
            <p>"It is unfathomable, father," at last Esther said softly, "and to think that His
               death was for even little Rosa, and the poor child knew nothing about it! I felt
               ashamed and speechless when she asked me why she had never been told before, having
               no reasonable answer whatever to give. I wish I could tell you with what earnestness
               she said, 'Are you real sure He paid the fare for everybody?' A fact so stupendous
               seemed quite beyond her power of comprehension." </p>
            <p>"Yes, daughter, His death included the fare for her <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="20" />as well as for you and for me. In every
               soul He sees a pearl of greatest price." </p>
            <p>"But Rosa left before I could explain anything to her about the way of salvation.
               Perhaps she will find no one to tell her, and her mother is almost dead. Oh, that I
               knew where she lives! All she needs is some one to guide her, then perhaps she would
               lead her mother and grandpa, and even Mrs. Gray into the light of His love. </p>
            <p>"Why is it, father, that so few Christians speak of Jesus to those whom they meet?
               They talk fluently of everything else, but the mentioning of His name seemingly
               paralyzes their tongues. This city is full of churches, with many thousands who
               profess to be the Lord's, yet Rosa in reality has never heard of Him. Every day of
               her life, as she goes upon the street, or is in a car, she comes into contact with
               some one who might lead her precious little soul to Christ. Just one moment of
               conversation would help her so, and is it possible that there is none who cares? Why
               is it? How can those who know Him truly be so utterly indifferent?" </p>
            <p>"My child, you ask me what I cannot answer. I spend many hours of prayer and study
               upon every sermon I preach, and seek to deliver it in the power of the Holy Spirit.
               Then after having cast myself utterly upon Him, it is simply crushing to know that at
                  <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="21" />times the message falls
               upon deaf ears. The tide of worldliness sweeping over the churches is at the root of
               the whole matter. Many to whom I preach are saved, but oh, so few surrendered! They
               want just enough of Christ to help them in times of trouble, to make sure of heaven
               being their ultimate goal, and just as much of this world as they can possibly carry
               along. It is their ambition to be His for eternity, but not for time. Oh, that they
               might know the unspeakable joy of a consecrated life, and of leading souls to Him!
               After once experiencing it, the charms of this world sink into utter insignificance,
               while the realities of the next become more and more certain. </p>
            <p>"The weight of my responsibility well nigh crushes me at times, for the Lord knows
               that I want to lead His people aright. How I yearn for absolute surrender upon the
               part of myself and of my church! When I remember Christ's words, 'Out of the
               abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh,' it makes me fear that many, indeed, of
               this generation shall say in vain at that day, Lord, Lord! It is a fearful thing for
               those who profess to know Him, to go up into His presence, leaving behind some still
               groping in darkness because of their unfaithfulness. If it is possible now for the
               Saviour ever to be unhappy, surely lukewarm Christians must pain Him the most." </p>
            <p>"Father, I want to find Rosa. If I had been more <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="22" />eager for her soul and for the glory of
               the Lord, I should have left the car and followed her. How can I begin the search? It
               seems so utterly impossible, yet I must." </p>
            <p>"My darling, it would be folly for you to try to find this child, but let us ask God
               to send her to us. He can direct in some way. He sees her this very moment, and sees
               us as well." </p>
            <p>A new and radiant light flooded Esther's face with joy, as they arose from their
               knees. </p>
            <p>"I am sure He will hear us, father, dear," she said, "for it was by no mere chance I
               saw her today. The Lord's directing hand was in it. He will, I know, forgive my
               unfaithfulness and open another opportunity. </p>
            <p>"Let us sing 'The Home of the Soul', father. How mother loved that song, when she
               knew that soon she would behold the beauties of the place!" </p>
            <p>The two voices, the one a sweet soprano, the other a fine tenor, blended in the
               old-time hymn: </p>
            <d:poem>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"I will sing you a song of that beautiful land, </l>

                  <l>The far away home of the soul, </l>

                  <l>Where no storms ever beat on that glittering strand, </l>

                  <l>While the years of eternity roll." </l>

               </d:stanza>
            </d:poem>
            <p>At the conclusion of the song, Esther kissed her father and quietly left the room. </p>

            <!-- End of level2-->
         </section>
         <section>
            <h>III. ROSA'S MOTHER MOVES.</h>
            <p>"Miss Browning, here's your steak I broiled fer you and some toast and tea. I fixed
               some fer Rosa, too you're so mighty queer, I knew you wouldn't eat unless she had
               some. I can't afford to buy her any more, and there ain't many that'd done it this
               time. I have to work awful hard fer all I git." </p>
            <p>"Thank you, Mrs. Gray, you are very kind, but," she added softly, lest Rosa who had
               run in to speak to grandpa might hear, "if only I knew what would become of her! Oh,
               my poor child! how can I bear to leave her, and what will her future be?" </p>
            <p>The moans of the poor, tortured mother, whose life was fast ebbing away, were most
               piteous. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="24" />"Now, Mis' Browning, don't
               take on so; chirk up a bit! She's plenty old enough to work and make her own livin'.
               Of course you couldn't expect me to say I'd keep her. Land sakes! Grandpa's all I can
               manage now, and he's gittin' worse and more tryin' every day. Why, jest this mornin'
               when I wuz that busy I didn't know what to do a-finishin' up that sewin', what should
               he do but stumble ag'in the coal pail and upset the whole thing right on the floor,
               and jest after I'd scrubbed, too! Then I thought I'd git rid of him a few minutes by
               sendin' him to the grocery. Of course I never trust him with a cent of money. They
               know him at the corner grocery, so it's all right; but it all comes of my credit
               a-bein' so good, that's the reason. Well, I told him it wuz not necessary fer him to
               be gone but fifteen minutes, but when he wuz gone twenty, I had to put my work down
               and go after him. I'd better have gone in the first place. That's always the way when
               I trust him fer anything, it jest makes it that much harder fer me in the end. I had
               to go clean down the stairs, and in some way twisted my ankle, so I ain't got over it
               yet; then I saw him a-comin', but that slow, it made me real provoked. If he'd jest
               a-hurried up a little, it would have saved me all that trouble. He said he wuz tired,
               but I think I wuz the one to be tired, a-hurryin' down them steps so, and a-gittin'
               hurt, too. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="25" />"Land sakes, Mis' Browning,
               I'd think you could see I have my hands more'n full now, though I don't wonder you
               would like to have Rosa brought up by me. I could train her mighty well, so as she'd
               know how to do somethin'. She's old enough to work, and I'll keep an eye on her and
               correct her whenever she needs it, and that'll be often. I'd think you'd ought to be
               satisfied with that. There ain't many that'd take sech an interest in a homeless
               little waif, I can tell you. </p>
            <p>"You eat your supper now, and I'll tell Rosa to come home. That's one thing she'll
               have to quit, a-wastin' so much time. What she sees in grandpa is more'n I can tell,
               fer he ain't got a bit of sense. Often in the night he wakes me up a-hollerin' and
               a-carryin' on a-thinkin' he's a boy ag'in. There's not many as patient as I am, or
               they wouldn't put up with it." </p>
            <p>Every word was a knife thrust through the sensitive, bleeding heart of the distracted
               mother. </p>
            <p>"Oh," she thought, "that some one in this great, crowded city might love my darling,
               and that she need not fall into the hands of this woman! </p>
            <p>"Mrs. Gray," she asked excitedly, and with an effort controlling the great dry sobs
               which were choking her, "won't you promise me one thing? Won't you keep Rosa at least
               till spring? What can my baby do without <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator"
                  value="26" />a home and without a mother, especially when the weather is so
               bitterly cold? The mere thought of such a possibility drives me insane with fear and
               grief. She can run errands for you, and grandpa loves her so. Do not deny me, for I
               am almost dead!" </p>
            <p>Mrs. Gray half staggered backward, for never before had she heard Mrs. Browning speak
               with such intensity. The dark eyes riveted upon her conquered even this unfeeling
               heart, and before realizing the import of her words, granted the request. "But," she
               added in the same breath, "there ain't many that'd do it, I can tell you that." </p>
            <p>"And be gentle with her, Mrs. Gray. She is so affectionate, she will miss her mother
               and the love I have always bestowed upon her." </p>
            <p>Thinking that other promises still more difficult to fulfill might be exacted, Mrs.
               Gray hastily left the room. </p>
            <p>"Thank God," the mother murmured falling back upon her pillow, "my baby will have
               food and shelter at least till spring, but how she will miss the love!" </p>
            <p>The hot tears began coursing down the flushed cheeks, causing Rosa to give a cry of
               alarm as she stepped up to the bedside. </p>
            <p>"Mother dear, do you feel worse? Why do you cry?"</p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="27" />"My darling, mother is tired
               now and cannot talk. Pull the little table up by the bed, then if I can eat some
               supper, we shall talk afterward. There is something I want to tell you." </p>
            <p>Mechanically she obeyed, weighted beneath the feeling that something dreadful was
               about to happen. The trembling of the tiny hands and twitching of the delicate face
               betrayed a heart suffering which a child of her tender years should never know. </p>
            <p>The odor of the steak, while being broiled, had given Rosa an appetite, for her
               dinner had consisted only of boiled potatoes. Now, however, that mother apparently
               did not relish her supper, it seemed that every mouthful would choke her. </p>
            <p>With a feeling of relief, the supper things at last were cleared away, and Rosa sat
               down by the sufferer, taking her hot thin hand within her own. </p>
            <p>"You need not talk, mother, if you do not feel like it, but I do so want to know
               about the moving, and you won't go without me, will you? But oh, I have such good
               news, I must tell you the very first thing! Mebbe it will change your plans and make
               it easier to know what to do. </p>
            <p>"I saw a lovely lady today, and she told me about a beautiful land some place, where
               folks never cough no more, and they don't have to pay rent, and they have
                  <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="28" />all they want to eat. And
               she said, too, that it don't cost nothing to go, nor after you get there, 'cause
               Jesus paid all the fare a long time ago. I wish I knew where to find Jesus, so He
               could explain all about it. I had to leave the car before the lady could tell me the
               way. I think He must be so good to pay the fare for everybody. There's no mistake,
               'cause she said something about God so loving the world. I don't know what she meant,
               but it was so pretty. I know I'd love Jesus so, if I could only find Him, and He'd
               tell us how to go, I'm sure He would. </p>
            <p>"Oh, mother, why do you cry so much? Don't feel so, for I'll try my very best to find
               out the way, then we'll both go. It will be so nice, won't it, for you not to have a
               cough no more? And mebbe we can manage to get off before the rent is due again." </p>
            <p>The anxious little nurse, old beyond her years, tenderly kissed the pallid brow,
               repeating soothingly the assurance that in some way she would find out how to reach
               this beautiful land. </p>
            <p>"O God," at last the invalid faltered after several minutes of silence, "forgive me
               and take me to that beautiful land, for Jesus' sake, and care for my darling! </p>
            <p>"Rosa dear, my breath is growing very short, but I must tell you something. You are
               too young to know <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="29" />what it all
               means now, but try to remember, and sometime you will understand. </p>
            <p>"Just ten years ago today I was married to your father, Harold Browning; and you are
               so like him, precious. </p>
            <p>"I was left an orphan at the age of fourteen, and from that time till the day of
               marriage, made my living by clerking in a down-town store. Your father, too, was
               alone in the world, and how we loved each other! </p>
            <p>"We rented a small furnished flat, which to me was a paradise. Your father was a
               bookkeeper on a comfortable salary, and for a time all went well. At the end of the
               second year you were born, and then our joy knew no bounds. Every evening while
               holding you in his arms, we would plan for the future, you being the center of
               everything. There was not a shadow over our lives, till one morning he was not able
               to go to work. In a few hours he became so very ill that in great alarm I summoned
               the doctor. Then followed weeks of suspense, the days being divided between hope and
               fear, till at last all thought of his recovery was given up. My anguish was too deep
               for tears. I went around as one stunned, not knowing at times what I was about. Your
               dear father tried to comfort me, pointing me to Jesus whom he loved intensely, but
               who I said was cruel to allow <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="30"
                />our little home nest thus ruthlessly to be broken up. </p>
            <p>"What happened the last days of his life to me is a blank, for I myself was very ill.
               When I recovered and paid all the bills, there was not one cent left for us. I could
               hold the flat no longer, so moved here on Burton street, making our living, as you
               know, darling, by the day's work. It has been very hard, for often I have felt unable
               to be out of bed; but then I could not let my Rosa suffer." </p>
            <p>The intervals when the poor heartbroken woman had to stop to regain her breath, were
               growing more frequent. </p>
            <p>"But, dearest," she continued, and in her earnestness she raised herself partly up,
               "the worst of all has been that I have tried to carry the burden alone. Your father
               told me that I must be brave for your sake, and that Jesus would help me; but I would
               not let Him. </p>
            <p>"Last night and today I have been praying much, and now, thank God, it is all right!" </p>
            <p>Rosa wondered at the expression of joy flooding her mother's face, immediately
               followed by one of deepest grief. </p>
            <p>"Bend closer, darling, my voice is becoming so weak that you cannot hear! I am so
               sorry that I did not do as your father said, and have never taught you <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="31" />of Jesus, and now it is—too late!—I'm
               glad—the lady—told you.—Yes,—He paid—the fare!—I'm—going—to move—now—to
               that—beautiful land!" </p>
            <p>"Oh, mother," sobbed Rosa, beginning to realize a little of the import of her words,
               "please, oh, please don't leave me! What could I ever do without you? Nobody loves me
               but you and grandpa, and I just can't stand it, if you go away." </p>
            <p>With her last atom of strength, the dying mother kissed her child, whispering just so
               that Rosa could hear: </p>
            <p>"Find someone—to tell you—the way,—and come—to that—beautiful—land—where you
               will—find Jesus—and mother!" </p>
            <p>So calmly did she fall back upon her pillow that Rosa, though awe-struck, thought she
               was sleeping. Still clasping the thin hand, she noticed the chill. Cautiously, lest
               she might disturb the sleeper, she slipped off her little flannel skirt, the last
               article made by her mother, and wrapped the cold hands within its folds. The scant
               coverings she also tucked up more closely and put their last bit of coal upon the
               fire. </p>
            <p>Till midnight she sat by the bed, wondering why mother was so very still, and why she
               was growing so cold. At last, being able to endure the suspense <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="32" />no longer, stepping across the hall,
               she called for Mrs. Gray. </p>
            <p>"Land sakes, child, why ain't you in bed this time of night?"</p>
            <p>"Please, Mis' Gray, I'd like to borrow a comfort, 'cause mother's so awful cold, and
               I can't get her warm." </p>
            <p>"Well, when a body's as accommodatin' as I am, I 'spose they must expect to be
               bothered any time of day or night, too. I'll git up and see what your ma wants. Glad
               of one thing, she ain't kept me awake by her coughin' tonight, anyway; but it comes
               from me fixin' her a decent supper, I reckon." </p>
            <p>Mrs. Gray stepped to the door of Mrs. Browning's room, but something impelled her to
               stop. A fear seized her, while involuntarily she clutched Rosa's trembling hand. </p>
            <p>There was no light in the room, save that which shone from across the hall, the faint
               rays falling directly over the motionless form upon the bed. </p>
            <p>"Mis' Browning," she cautiously asked, "do you want anything?"</p>
            <p>"Mother doesn't hear, Mis' Gray," said Rosa sobbing violently and throwing herself
               within the cold arms, kissing over and over the lips hitherto so responsive to her
               own. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="33" />"Mother dear, don't you hear
               me? Oh, wake up, please do! I want you so. I don't know the way, and will get lost to
               go alone." </p>
            <p>"Rosa," said Mrs. Gray almost gently, "git up and go and stay with grandpa till I
               tell you to come in here, and don't you come before. I'll have to go down them steps
               ag'in fer an undertaker." </p>
            <p>"What is an undertaker, Mis' Gray, and what do they do? Will they take mother to the
               beautiful land?" </p>
            <p>"Didn't you hear me tell you to go in and stay with grandpa? So go right this minute,
               and ask no more questions. You do beat all fer askin' questions, anyhow. You might as
               well learn now as any time to mind, since I have to keep you till spring. I ain't the
               woman to go back on my word, but there ain't many but what would, a-promisin' under
               the circumstances." </p>
            <p>The little heart was nearly crushed with a feeling of perplexity and of indescribable
               dread, but, after all, there was some comfort in being alone with grandpa. </p>
            <p>Stealing softly into his room, she found him sitting by the stove; and climbing up
               into his lap, pillowing her tired head upon his shoulder, the two lonely children,
               soothing each other, were soon fast asleep. </p>

         </section>
         <section>
            <h>IV. LIFE WITH MRS. GRAY.</h>
            <p>The events of the next few days were like a troubled dream to Rosa, as she in vain
               endeavored to comprehend the meaning of all the mysterious things going on about her.
               Only once was she allowed to look upon the silent sleeper. That was just before the
               arrival of the great black carriage, which, she was sure, would take her mother to
               the beautiful land. </p>
            <p>"Rosa ain't goin' to the burial, I can tell you that," announced Mrs. Gray to a
               neighbor, "or she'd be a-hollerin' in her sleep all winter. I've been broke of my
               rest so much that I ain't goin' to be bothered with her any more'n I can help from
               now on. I didn't promise to keep her only till spring, but I can make her run errands
               and sich, so it won't cost me a great sight. I <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="35" />can't afford it no other way, and Mis'
               Browning was unreasonable, anyhow, to ask it of me." </p>
            <p>Rosa and grandpa stood hand in hand, watching the small procession until it
               disappeared around the corner. </p>
            <p>"Grandpa," queried Rosa in a tearful voice, "do you know where that beautiful land is
               where folks never cough no more, and where they don't have to pay rent? That's where
               mother's going, and she told me to find out the way, so I could go too." </p>
            <p>"'Pears like I'd ought to know, child, fer that's where Tom went. I can't think much
               somehow, but, Rosa," he added tenderly, drawing her up closer to his side, "I don't
               want you to go and leave me, fer I'm so lonesome. Sary's a good woman, yes, a very
               good woman, but it seems like I need you, too, dearie." </p>
            <p>"Grandpa, if we'd start out together, don't you think we could find it? Folks have
               all they want to eat there, and I'm hungry now." </p>
            <p>"Why, yes, yes, mebbe we could! Some way I'm gittin' homesick. I don't like it here
               in the city, and it seems like I used to know more about that land than I do now.
               Since poor Tom got killed, I can't remember no how. </p>
            <p>"Sometimes in the night I git that happy, but if I make a little noise, Sary wakes me
               up, 'cause it bothers <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="36" />her,
               then that spoils it all. I think I'm back in the country ag'in, and the church bell
               is a-ringin' of a Sunday mornin'. Tom's mother and me start out from the little
               cottage, and I'm a-carryin' Tom. We walk down the cool grassy lane with the brook
               a-runnin' on one side, and the trees is a-wavin' in the soft breeze, and the birds is
               a-singin', and Tom's mother stops to pick some wild roses. And the little white
               meetin' house with the steeple a-p'intin' straight up. My Rosa, I wish you could see
               it, and with vines a-growin' all over it! I can 'most git it, then it slips away
               ag'in. If I could jest be inside of that meetin' house once more, it would all come
               straight, I know, fer there they used to talk and sing about that land and Jesus." </p>
            <p>"Yes, grandpa, you know it was Jesus that paid the fare. Wasn't He kind to do that?
               'cause if He hadn't poor folks couldn't go." </p>
            <p>"Yes, mighty kind, mighty kind!</p>
            <p>"Rosa," after a pause, "come real close," and the faded eyes sparkled with a new
               thought; "I want to whisper somethin' so nobody'll hear. The very first day Sary's
               away, let's start out, and mebbe we can find some one to tell us how to go. Will you,
               child?" </p>
            <p>"Oh, yes, grandpa, good! then we'll find mother."</p>
            <p>In her delight she clapped her hands for very joy.</p>
            <p>"Sh! sh! child, Sary might hear, and that would <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="37" />spoil it all, though of course Sary's a
               good woman, yes, a very good woman. You won't tell, will you?" </p>
            <p>"No, no, grandpa, this'll be our secret. I'm just sure there must be lots of folks
               that can tell us, for the fare is paid for everybody, and they're going all the time.
               But I do wish we could find that pretty lady again I saw on the car." </p>
            <p>"Yes, dearie, I wish so too, but I think we'll find it anyhow. I'm a-gittin' so very
               homesick, we jest must." </p>
            <p>"Sing about that land, won't you, grandpa?"</p>
            <p>"All right, you git the fiddle. That's the only song I can remember. They used to
               sing it in the little white meetin' house with the steeple a-p'intin' straight up.
               Wish I could remember more, but I can't." </p>
            <p>In a quavery voice he sang many times over the grand old hymn:</p>
            <d:poem>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"I will sing you a song of that beautiful land, </l>

                  <l>The far away home of the soul, </l>

                  <l>Where no storms ever beat on that glittering strand, </l>

                  <l>While the years of eternity roll. </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>Oh, that home of the soul in my visions and dreams, </l>

                  <l>Its bright, jasper walls I can see, </l>

                  <l>Till I fancy but thinly the vail intervenes </l>

                  <l>Between that fair city and me! </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>That unchangeable home is for you and for me, </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="38" />
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>Where Jesus of Nazareth stands; </l>

                  <l>The King of all kingdoms forever is He, </l>

                  <l>And He holdeth our crowns in His hands. </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>Oh, how sweet it will be in that beautiful land, </l>

                  <l>So free from all sorrow and pain, </l>

                  <l>With songs on our lips and with harps in our hands, </l>

                  <l>To meet one another again!" </l>

               </d:stanza>
            </d:poem>
            <p>"That must be the place, grandpa, for it says Jesus is there, and that we'll meet one
               another again." </p>
            <p>"Yes, yes, child, it's the place, I'm mighty sure of that, and I'm so glad we're
               a-goin' to find it. I'll like it so much better than the city. I wonder I ain't gone
               before." </p>
            <p>The two sang and talked till the twilight began to fall, then they heard Mrs. Gray
               shuffling up the stairs. </p>
            <p>"Now don't fergit and tell, Rosa," hurriedly whispered grandpa.</p>
            <p>"Oh, no indeed, and we'll go the very first chance we have. Won't mother be glad to
               see us?" </p>
            <p>"Land sakes, Rosa, you look and act a heap like you'd jest lost your ma. I heard that
               fiddle and you a-singin' with grandpa long before I got up the steps. But it is real
               lucky fer you, though, that I'll have you to manage till spring. You'll learn how to
               do somethin' a-stayin' here with me, or I'll miss my guess. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="39" />"Why ain't you got a brisker
               fire started up fer supper? Do it right this minute. It'll be somethin' new fer you
               to have a cooked meal every day, and sometimes two or three of them. But you'll have
               to earn them first, or eat by yourself, and jest what you can git. </p>
            <p>"I ain't a-goin' to keep you fer nothin'. Hurry up now, fer I'm cold, and my ankle's
               'most a-killin' me. Father'd ought to be shook yet, fer causin' me so much trouble.
               No tellin' how much longer it'll pain me, and I shouldn't wonder if it'd lay me up." </p>
            <p>Thus rudely was Rosa's reverie broken in upon, bringing her face to face with her
               present dingy surroundings in general, and with Mrs. Gray in particular. Her first
               impulse was to run home, then in agony she remembered that her mother was not there. </p>
            <p>Patiently she worked away till the fire was started. Mrs. Gray's bulky form in the
               meantime was swinging energetically back and forth in the one rocking chair of her
               two-room apartment, while her voluble tongue wagged mercilessly on. </p>
            <p>"You can cook them potatoes and fry some mush and make me a cup of tea. You and
               father can drink water; tea ain't good fer children nohow, ha, ha! </p>
            <p>"Ugh, this fire feels good! I'm glad I ain't where your ma is tonight."</p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="40" />"Why, Mis' Gray," half sobbed
               Rosa, "didn't mother go to the beautiful land?" </p>
            <p>"You be still and git supper, and don't ask me no questions!"</p>
            <p>"There, there, dearie, don't cry! Of course your ma went there." It was grandpa who
               spoke. </p>
            <p>"A heap you know about it, father, and I jest want you to keep still, too! </p>
            <p>"Look out there! Don't you spatter no grease a-fryin' that mush, or you'll wish you
               hadn't. I believe in the good old-fashioned rod, and there's one stuck up over that
               door, handy like. See it?" </p>
            <p>To her great dismay, looking in the direction indicated, Rosa beheld a cruel whip,
               the first one ever intended for her. Her little frame shook so violently from fear
               that grandpa could endure it no longer. </p>
            <p>"Tut, tut, Sary; Rosa ain't the child to need no whippin', and don't skeer the poor
               lamb so. </p>
            <p>"Never mind, dearie," reaching out for her a withered hand, "Sary don't mean it;
               Sary's a good woman, yes, a very good woman." </p>
            <p>"Father, I want you to remember right now that you ain't to put no say in when I
               correct her. There ain't but one boss here, and that's me, so there! Do you
               understand? I 'spose not, though, fer you ain't got no sense. You're tryin' enough,
               goodness knows, <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="41" />that there
               ain't many but what'd use the rod on you." </p>
            <p>So blinded by tears that she could not see what she was doing, by accident Rosa
               dropped a piece of the fried mush upon the floor. </p>
            <p>"There!" shrieked Mrs. Gray, "what did I tell you? I'm a-goin' to lick you this very
               minute, now you jest see. I guess you'll learn to mind after I've done it a few
               times." </p>
            <p>"Grandpa!" and with a bound Rosa jumped into the old man's outstretched arms, while
               tears chased each other in quick succession down his faded cheeks. </p>
            <p>Making an effort to arise hastily from her chair, Mrs. Gray with a sharp cry of pain,
               suddenly sank backward again. </p>
            <p>"Oh, my ankle's plum give out—I can't take one step! But you never mind, I'll lick
               you some other time, and you needn't fergit it neither. Git right down and clean up
               that mush, and fix some hot water fer me to put my foot in." </p>
            <p>Seeing the helpless condition of the tyrant, Rosa waited long enough before obeying
               to kiss grandpa, and for him to whisper encouragingly: </p>
            <p>"Never mind, dearie; we'll go the very first chance we have, and if we can't do no
               better, we'll run off." </p>
            <p>With some degree of composure, Rosa performed her tasks, for evidently, judging from
               the groans of <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="44" />the patient,
               the promised "lickin'" would be indefinitely postponed. </p>
            <p>While eating supper, Mrs. Gray divided her attentions about equally between the two
               helpless victims of her wrath. The sprained ankle was entirely due to the fact that
               grandpa was gone twenty minutes instead of fifteen, and that she, obliging woman that
               she was, took it upon herself to make all the arrangements for Mrs. Browning, instead
               of looking after her own welfare. Not many could be found who would do half as much
               for others as she. </p>
            <p>The grease from that mush would stay in the floor all winter, seriously injuring her
               reputation of being the best housekeeper in the thickly populated building. She never
               could endure dirt and disorder, though poverty-striken from the day she married Tom
               Gray. </p>
            <p>On the whole, Rosa was so thoroughly miserable that very little supper could she eat.
               The thought that she and grandpa would soon find the beautiful land and mother, was
               all that gave her even the slightest ray of hope. "But," she added mentally, "I am
               sure mother would tell me to stay and take care of Mis' Gray till she can walk again.
               She always did do more talking than anything else, mother said so, mebbe she won't
               whip me." </p>
            <p>The evening was long and gloomy, but Rosa was <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="45" />kept busily employed, carrying out the
               peremptory commands of the cripple. She bathed and tenderly rubbed the offending
               ankle till her arm ached cruelly. </p>
            <p>At last, with a sigh of relief, wrapping herself up in a blanket and lying down upon
               the floor, she dreamed till morning of mother, the beautiful land, and of Jesus who
               paid the fare. </p>
            <p>For three weeks Mrs. Gray was unable to take a step except by using a crutch, the
               pain at times being so severe that sewing was out of the question. </p>
            <p>Her slender savings not being sufficient to meet the emergency of the case, Rosa in
               her spare moments was obliged to run errands, tend babies while the mothers were out
               working, or to do anything else chancing to come her way. </p>
            <p>Her allowance of food often was meager, though never once did she complain. Every day
               she was growing more thin and pale, her eyes more large and lustrous, while her heart
               was almost breaking. </p>
            <p>Night after night the swollen ankle had to be gently rubbed, or Mrs. Gray could not
               sleep. No word of praise ever escaped the cruel lips, but fretting, scolding, and
               threats of the much talked of "lickin'" for that grease spot upon the floor were the
               only reward the weary little worker ever received. </p>
            <p>There was one, however, though his mind was badly <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="46" />shattered, who saw and understood,
               causing the feeble old man to suffer quite as intensely as did the child. </p>
            <p>They could snatch opportunities only now and then for a word, fearing that the
               ever-vigilant Mrs. Gray might discover their cherished secret. </p>
            <p>"Be brave, dearie," grandpa would sometimes whisper, "the very first chance, you
               know!" Then Rosa's pensive face would light up with a smile angelic, reflecting some
               of the very beauty itself of the land of which they were so earnestly thinking. </p>
            <p>One Thursday afternoon, just as Mrs. Gray was beginning to walk again, the postman
               stopped with a letter, a rare occurrence. </p>
            <p>"Land sakes, who can it be from?" she exclaimed, scrutinizing the envelope quite long
               enough to have read the letter through. </p>
            <p>"I'd like to awful well," at last she soliloquized, "but don't 'spose it'd be safe to
               leave grandpa and Rosa here alone. No tellin' what they'd be up to. There ain't many
               that'd be as self-sacrificin' as I am, and keep an old man that ain't got a drop of
               your own blood, then take in as good as a street waif, too. If it wuzn't fer them,
               I'd do it, I jest would!" </p>
            <p>Rosa's curiosity was aroused, but experience had taught her the futility of asking
               questions. </p>
            <p>"Rosa," commanded the speaker, "bring me that tin can up there on the shelf. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="47" />"I guess I could manage the
               streetcar fare," she announced a few minutes later, counting over several times
               Rosa's earnings in pennies, nickels and dimes. </p>
            <p>"My old neighbor over on the south side wants me to come tomorrow and stay till
               Monday. Bein' that I've had it so awful hard, I jest guess I'll do it, and you can
               git along the best way you can. Let me see: I'll go tomorrow afternoon, and be gone
               all day Saturday and Sunday and till late Monday afternoon. I'll leave you fifteen
               cents apiece to live on, and I guess you won't starve." </p>
            <p>Instinctively grandpa and Rosa cast a glance at each other. At last their opportunity
               had come, and a better one by far than for which they had dared to hope! </p>
            <p>The time intervening between the reception of the letter and her departure, Mrs. Gray
               spent mostly in giving directions to her two charges, as she delighted to call them. </p>
            <p>After having gone down the first flight of stairs, she called back:</p>
            <p>"Rosa, I'll lick you sure if you git another speck of grease on that there floor,
               while I'm gone." </p>
            <p>But Rosa heeded not. Tomorrow she and grandpa would start for the beautiful land and
               mother, for Jesus had paid all the fare. </p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <h>V. THE WAY SOUGHT.</h>
            <p>Early the next morning Rosa and grandpa were up, eagerly preparing for the events of
               the day, their every motion evidencing a subdued excitement, while joy beamed from
               their eyes. </p>
            <p>"I'm going to make you some tea, grandpa, 'cause it's cold, and I think you'll feel
               better to drink it. Mis' Gray told me I shouldn't touch it, but since we're going
               away, I guess it won't make no difference. We may have to travel a good ways, you
               know. Mother used to drink tea, when we could afford it, before starting out to work
               all day. My, ain't I glad we're going to find mother! And she won't be coughing no
               more. I want to see her so bad. Of course Mis' Gray has been good to give me a home,
               but I'd rather be with mother. She's different some way, and I love her so. It seems
               so long since she went away." </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="49" />"Thank you, dearie, fer this
               tea; it's real bracin' like, and I can't remember when I've had none before Tom used
               to git it fer me, and anything else I wanted. </p>
            <p>"Yes, I'm mighty glad we're a-goin', mighty glad, fer I'm a-gittin' homesicker all
               the time. I think we'll find Tom, too, and Tom's mother. There's a lot I want to tell
               'em. Sary's so busy, she don't have no time to talk to me. </p>
            <p>"Last night I dreamed ag'in that I wuz in the little white meetin' house with the
               steeple a-pintin' straight up. The green vines a-wavin' in the breeze wuz a-growin'
               all over it, and the roses smelled so pretty. And the man wuz a-readin' out of the
               Book, Rosa. Wish I could read, then I'd know it fer myself." </p>
            <p>"What was he reading about, grandpa?"</p>
            <p>"Dunno as I can tell you, child, only somethin' about a river, and a tree by it, and
               fruit, and the folks don't git sick no more, and—well, I can't tell you, Rosa, but
               hurry up, let's start! When we git there, we'll know all about it then." </p>
            <p>"Here, grandpa, put this bread in your pocket, please. P'rhaps we'll need it." </p>
            <p>"I'll take it fer you, Rosa, if you say so, but I don't think we'll need it. 'Pears
               like the man said somethin' about their not gittin' hungry no more, nor thirsty." </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="50" />"But then mebbe we'll want it
               on the way." </p>
            <p>"All right, all right, Rosa, but are you 'most ready? Seems like I can't wait." </p>
            <p>"Yes, I'm ready now, but I'm so 'fraid you'll be cold, grandpa, dear."</p>
            <p>"No, no, child, we'll soon git there."</p>
            <p>The two children trudged down the three long flights of steps, the younger leading
               the older lest he should trip and fall. </p>
            <p>The morning was dreary, with a cold wind blowing and with snow flakes scurrying
               through the air. Both being insufficiently clad, they were shivering before having
               gone a block. </p>
            <p>"'Tis mighty cold, ain't it, dearie? I had no idee about it; but then we won't mind,
               jest so we git there." </p>
            <p>"Yes, grandpa, but I hope it won't take us long, for the wind blows so awful hard. It
               used to make mother cough to be out in a wind like this. </p>
            <p>"The big black carriage that came after her, went 'round this corner, so we'll go
               this way too. I'm sure nobody on Burton street knows the way anyhow. I'd think they
               would, though, when the fare's all paid; but p'rhaps they've never been told about
               it. </p>
            <p>"When we see a pretty lady dressed fine, we'll ask her, for I guess she'd know; but
               then it's for poor folks, too. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="51" />"I wonder why nobody ever
               told me about Jesus before? I'll be so glad when I see Him." </p>
            <p>Tenderly clasping each other by the hand, they walked for blocks, meeting hundreds of
               people, though none of them appealed to Rosa's fancy. She was looking for a beautiful
               girl with blue eyes and a blue suit, who would look down upon her with a smile. A
               feeling of uncertainty was beginning to depress her, but to grandpa she continued to
               talk hopefully. </p>
            <p>At last realizing that he was becoming very tired, she determined to wait no longer
               before inquiring the way. Singling out of the jostling crowd a well-dressed woman
               with a fur cloak, which Rosa thought looked so warm, she stepped up to her, and said: </p>
            <p>"Please, ma'am, grandpa and me want to go to the beautiful land where folks don't
               cough no more. Mother's gone, and Jesus paid all the fare, and it don't cost nothing
               to live there, neither. Won't you please tell us the way?" </p>
            <p>"What a very singular question!" was the unfeeling reply, the haughty face relaxing
               not at all as the woman passed on. </p>
            <p>"I think she didn't understand, grandpa," said the disappointed child, "but I'll try
               again. There's a lady dressed in blue. I'm pretty sure she'll know." </p>
            <p>In a tremulous voice the question was repeated.</p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="52" />"Why, you queer little girl!
               Are you talking about heaven?" </p>
            <p>"I don't know, ma'am, only it's where Jesus has paid the fare, and where there ain't
               no rent days to come 'round." </p>
            <p>"Really, I scarcely know what to say, only you and this poor old man ought not to be
               out on this cold day." </p>
            <p>"We thought we'd soon be there, ma'am, but 'tis dreadful cold," she replied, her
               slight frame shivering violently from head to foot. </p>
            <p>"Can't you tell us? We want to go so awful bad. I should think you could, since it's
               for everybody." </p>
            <p>"It is too cold and crowded to stand here and talk, child. Do you go to Sunday
               school?" </p>
            <p>"No, ma'am; what is Sunday school?"</p>
            <p>"You poor little heathen! Don't you know what Sunday schools are? They have them in
               all the churches. Find one and go tomorrow. They will tell you what you want better
               than I can. </p>
            <p>"Take this quarter and get something to eat, then go back home. You will meet no one
               on the street to help you." </p>
            <p>Having thus somewhat eased her conscience, this church-member of many years went on
               to complete her shopping. However, things did not go well the <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="53" />rest of the day. The wan face, the sad
               brown eyes and the pathetic earnestness of the little questioner were constantly
               before her. </p>
            <p>Stopping to see the church treasurer on her way home, she left a check for fifty
               dollars to be used in city mission work, feeling confident that at last her
               responsibility in the case was at an end. </p>
            <p>It was nearing the noon hour, and Rosa was hungry.</p>
            <p>"I think instead of eating that dry bread in your pocket, grandpa, that we'll get
               some warm sandwiches. You wait: I can get them in here, 'cause I was in one time
               before with mother." </p>
            <p>Very soon she returned, bringing with her their feast.</p>
            <p>"Let's go down this alley and sit on that box. I guess the p'licemen won't care." </p>
            <p>"All right, dearie, but it's a mighty long ways to the beautiful land, ain't it? I
               thought we'd surely be there by now, and I'm gittin' so tired and cold. I think if
               Tom knew we'd started, he'd come and meet us." </p>
            <p>While they were eating, Rosa was frightened to hear suddenly the abrupt question in a
               gruff voice, "What are you doing here?" and before her terrified eyes loomed a great
               policeman. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="54" />She, like most children of
               her class, feared instinctively these city protectors, and would have run, had it
               have not been for grandpa. </p>
            <p>"Oh," she replied, with as much dignity and composure as possible, "we are going to
               the beautiful land, and are just eating our sandwiches. It don't cost nothing to go,
               'cause God so loved the world and Jesus paid all the fare. Mother's gone, and folks
               don't cough no more there. You don't have to pay rent, and can have everything you
               want, too." </p>
            <p>So astonished was the policeman at this unexpected reply that he forgot to order them
               away. </p>
            <p>"Well, I never!" at last he ejaculated, being unable to think of anything more
               appropriate for the occasion. "But let me tell you, little girl, you and that old man
               want to turn in wherever you came from before dark, or you'll be more likely to go to
               the police station than to this beautiful land you're talking about." </p>
            <p>So saying, he started off upon his beat.</p>
            <p>The mere thought of spending the night at the police station so thoroughly terrorized
               Rosa that her heart for the instant almost stood still. </p>
            <p>Billy Bruce, the boy who lived next door to Mrs. Gray, had told her blood-curdling
               tales concerning his oft-repeated experiences in being locked up for the <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="55" />night, and, moreover, according to his
               criterion, he was always innocent of any misdemeanor. </p>
            <p>"But the worst part of all," he had confided, "is a goin' before the judge. You know
               the judge is the man what's made to git folks into trouble." </p>
            <p>What should she do? Her childish eyes could see that grandpa was about given out, but
               the mere thought of returning to Burton street filled her with a feeling akin to
               terror. </p>
            <p>"But," she argued, "Mis' Gray won't be home till Monday, and mebbe it's too far to
               the beautiful land that we can't get there today, anyhow. And I know mother'd feel
               awful if we'd get put in the p'lice station. </p>
            <p>"Say, grandpa," she suddenly inquired, "why didn't we ask that p'liceman the way?
               They're on purpose to tell folks how to go. I wish we had, but then I'm afraid to
               speak to another." </p>
            <p>"I don't know, child, but I wish we wuz there. I'm so cold and tired, and I want
               Tom." </p>
            <p>"I'll tell you, grandpa, let's go back and get warm and rested. You know there is
               some of that bushel of coal left Mis' Gray got the other day. Then tomorrow we can
               try once more. The lady said something about church and Sunday school, but I don't
               know what she meant. Mebbe we can find some <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator"
                  value="56" />yet to tell us, when it's for everybody. I'd think we could." </p>
            <p>"Jest as you say, dearie, jest as you say, but it 'pears like we must find it, 'cause
               I'm so homesick." </p>
            <p>Slowly they began retracing their steps, the old man leaning heavily with one hand
               upon the stick which served as a cane, and with the other clasping Rosa's. </p>
            <p>Turning a corner, they suddenly came face to face with a well-dressed gentleman who,
               Rosa thought, could certainly tell them. </p>
            <p>"Oh, say, mister," she said running up to his side, "won't you please—"</p>
            <p>"No, I won't, you little beggar, I have nothing for you."</p>
            <p>For the instant she was so surprised and indignant, that she could not answer, but,
               collecting herself, shouted after him: </p>
            <p>"We ain't either beggars, and I don't want no money. I just want to know the way to
               the beautiful land." </p>
            <p>But the man was lost in the crowd, and the weary, disappointed pilgrims started on. </p>
            <p>So frequently did they have to turn aside into some alley or secluded spot for
               grandpa to rest that Rosa became alarmed. What if night should overtake them,
               bringing to pass the policeman's direful prediction? </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="57" />She was so tired and cold,
               and her heart so heavy from repeated disappointments, that the tears began rolling
               down her pale cheeks. </p>
            <p>"What is it, my little girl?" unexpectedly some one gently asked.</p>
            <p>In unutterable surprise, she looked up into the face of another policeman who was
               smiling kindly upon her. </p>
            <p>Many a warm heart beats beneath the policeman's star, and Rosa's evident sorrow had
               aroused the sincere sympathy of this one. </p>
            <p>"You and the old man step up here out of the wind by this building, and tell me your
               trouble. Are you lost?" </p>
            <p>"No, sir, we ain't lost, but just can't find the way."</p>
            <p>"Not lost, but can't find the way? How is it? I don't understand. Maybe I can help
               you, if you will explain." </p>
            <p>At this Rosa broke into uncontrollable sobs, and for several minutes could not
               answer. </p>
            <p>At last, with many a pause, the whole story was told.</p>
            <p>"And oh," she added, with all the earnestness of which her intense nature was
               capable, "can you really tell us? Please, oh, please do, for I can't stand it any
               longer without mother, and she's looking for me, 'cause Jesus paid the fare. I just
               must go!" </p>

            <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="58" />

            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="60" />"Ah, sweet baby," he
               faltered, his massive frame shaking with emotion, "I've a mother in the beautiful
               land looking for me, too! </p>
            <p>"Long years ago I promised to meet her there, but, no, I've never found the way. I
               cannot tell you." </p>
            <p>"If the way's so hard to find, how do folks get there? And lots of them are going,
               for the lady said so. I do wish mother'd come back for grandpa and me"; and again the
               child broke into sobs. </p>
            <p>"Don't cry any more, little one. They say the way is easy to find. Let me think a
               minute; maybe I can help you after all. There's a big church on the corner there, and
               I know the pastor loves poor people. If you should go there tomorrow, he would tell
               you the way, I know. </p>
            <p>"Now cheer up, and get back to your home as soon as possible. It will be getting dark
               presently, and you will half freeze. I will walk down to the corner with you, and
               point out the church." </p>
            <p>Rosa's hopes were beginning to rise once more, but upon beholding the massive stone
               structure indicated by the policeman, she felt less sanguine. </p>
            <p>"Are you real sure, mister, we could find the way if we'd go in there?" at length she
               said. </p>
            <p>"Yes, I know it, for the pastor has wanted many times to teach me the way, and I
               wouldn't let him." </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="61" />Rosa had no idea who or what
               the pastor might be, and forgot to inquire, because of her unutterable surprise. </p>
            <p>It was simply unthinkable that any one could deliberately refuse the information
               which she and grandpa so earnestly coveted. </p>
            <p>"Mister p'liceman, why didn't you want to know the way?" she gasped, impulsively
               grasping his big, brawny hand. "Wouldn't you like to know now?" </p>
            <p>"Yes, little one, I would, and by God's help I will. But come, you must be gone! It
               is almost dark. I'll watch for you in the morning, and take you to the door. Be sure
               not to disappoint me. Goodbye!" </p>
            <p>That evening in the quiet of his room a wonderful thing happened.</p>
            <p>Tucked away in the bottom of his trunk was a Bible, given to him years before by his
               mother, when he was but a mere lad. This he brought forth, and till a late hour
               poured over its precious contents. Then falling upon his knees, this prodigal of many
               years found in Jesus the true way to the beautiful land. He Himself said that no man
               cometh unto the Father but by Him. And an unspeakable peace filled his soul. </p>
            <p>The last half mile of their walk seemed almost interminable both to Rosa and grandpa. </p>
            <p>As the darkness began to gather, every shadow to <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="62" />her excited imagination was transformed
               into a policeman coming to lock them up. </p>
            <p>After the trying experiences of the day, it was a relief to be back once more in the
               dingy rooms which they had expected never to see again. </p>
            <p>Rosa soon had a fire feebly burning in the little stove, then prepared a scanty
               supper, offset by another cup of tea for grandpa. </p>
            <p>The shabby couch she pulled up by the stove for him, and did all within her power to
               make him warm and comfortable. </p>
            <p>Sitting by his side and watching him solicitously, she was beginning to fear that he
               might not be able for the journey tomorrow, for without a doubt he was much
               exhausted. At last the tears began rolling down his face and fell upon her hand. </p>
            <p>"Oh, grandpa, what is it?" she asked, the tears coming to her own eyes. "You ain't
               sick, are you?" </p>
            <p>"No, no, dearie, but mighty dis'p'inted. I thought we'd be there tonight sure, and
               I'm so homesick! Too bad, too bad, ain't it, when the fare's all paid, and they're
               a-looking fer us? We wouldn't git hungry nor cold there, neither, nor tired." </p>
            <p>"Yes, but, grandpa dear, the p'liceman said we could find the way tomorrow in that
               great big building. Of course he must know, don't you think so?" </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="63" />"Say, Rosa," he asked
               excitedly, not noticing her question, and rising partly up, while his eyes sparkled
               with new hope, "I can't remember, but did it have a steeple a-p'intin' straight up?" </p>
            <p>"Yes, such a big one, grandpa. It must go pretty nearly to the sky."</p>
            <p>"Then it'll be all right, I'm mighty sure of that, but it 'pears like it'd ought to
               have green vines a-runnin' all over it, and with roses a-growin' 'round. Wuz there
               any?" </p>
            <p>"No, grandpa, for this is winter, you know. The roses won't be blooming outdoors now,
               but sometimes I see them in the stores." </p>
            <p>"And so we'll git there tomorrow, Rosa," he added dreamily, "and not be dis'p'inted
               no more! I'm so mighty glad, so mighty glad." </p>
            <p>Grandpa was asleep, but becoming more and more restless. His hands no longer were
               cold, but felt hot to Rosa, as she vainly endeavored to keep them covered. The
               flushed cheeks and rapid breathing convinced his faithful and experienced young nurse
               that it would be wise for her to sit by his side till morning. The hours were long
               and dreary, and at every sound her overtaxed nerves would cause her to start.
               Sometimes she was sure that a policeman was coming after them; and again Mrs. Gray
               was about to enter the <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="64" />room
               with a cruel whip in her hand. So certain was she once of hearing her mother call
               that she jumped to her feet to obey the summons. Then before her vision would stand a
               lovely girl dressed in blue, smiling down upon her and saying: </p>
            <p>"Jesus paid all the fare long ago."</p>
            <p>Toward morning grandpa grew more quiet. The little watcher dropped her head upon his
               pillow and fell asleep, dreaming that mother was holding her in her arms, softly
               singing as of yore. </p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="65" />
            <h>VI. THE WAY FOUND</h>
            <p>It was late before they awakened the next morning. Rosa, though not much rested
               herself, was delighted to see grandpa apparently so well. She could not remember ever
               before having seen him step so lightly around the room. His eyes were shining, and
               every few minutes he would sing snatches of his one song, while assisting her in the
               preparation of their light breakfast. </p>
            <p>"We're a-goin' to find it today, Rosa, I'm mighty sure, yes, mighty sure of that; and
               I'm so glad." </p>
            <p>"I hope so, grandpa dear."</p>
            <p>"Yes, we are, fer he said so."</p>
            <p>"Who said so?"</p>
            <p>"Why, Tom. Don't you remember? We seen him last night, Rosa. Surely you ain't fergot. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="66" />"We wuz a-crossin' the pretty
               brook on the bridge under the willers, when all to once Tom come a-runnin' up, and
               wuz so glad to see us. Jest then the bell on the little white meetin' house with the
               steeple a-p'intin' straight up begun a-ringin', and it sounded better'n music. Oh, it
               wuz so mighty sweet, Rosa! I can 'most hear it now. And when we got there, the people
               was a-singin' about the beautiful land. Everybody wuz so happy, 'cause the fare wuz
               paid and they all know'd the way. Tom he says, 'Don't be dis'p'inted no more, father,
               'cause you're a goin' to git there, and no mistake!' </p>
            <p>"Now, Rosa dear," he continued, while walking rapidly back and forth across the room,
               "let's git ready and start right off, and not lose no more time. </p>
            <p>"We're goin' to the big meetin' house today, didn't you say?"</p>
            <p>"Yes, grandpa, the one the p'liceman showed us, you know."</p>
            <p>"'Pears like we'd ought to fix up a little bit then. My shoes look most mighty bad,
               don't they? It might worry Tom some. I don't like to have him find out how poor I've
               been, but then it won't make no difference after we git there. </p>
            <p>"Say, do you think Sary would miss it, if I'd take some of her stove polish and black
               'em up a little?" </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="67" />"Oh, I don't believe she
               would." </p>
            <p>"Then I'll take jest a tiny bit, not that she'd care, fer Sary's a good woman, yes, a
               very good woman, but mighty partic'lar about her blackin'." </p>
            <p>Rosa patiently assisted in the process, but it would have been difficult for the
               aesthetic eye to have discovered the improvement. Grandpa was satisfied, and that was
               enough. </p>
            <p>"I don't want you to get cold like you did yesterday, grandpa. The wind's blowing
               hard. Wish you had more to put 'round you." </p>
            <p>"Well, I ain't got it, dearie, but I don't mind, fer we're a-goin' to git there
               today. Tom'll look after me then." </p>
            <p>"Here, you take this: it'll help a little," and she slipped from her own neck a
               well-worn muffler formerly belonging to her mother. She carefully pinned together his
               thin shabby coat, for the buttons long since were gone, and wrapped the muffler about
               his neck and face. </p>
            <p>Her own clothing, since mother moved, had grown threadbare and ragged, forming but
               little protection against the cold, cutting winds. </p>
            <p>Their hearts, notwithstanding all outward difficulties and the disappointments of the
               preceding day, were buoyant with hope as they started out once more upon their
               pilgrimage. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="68" />Their one friend, the
               policeman, saw them coming and met them a short distance from their destination. </p>
            <p>"Good morning, grandpa and my little lady," he cheerily called, "I have been
               expecting you for some time. I had almost begun to fear that something had prevented
               your coming. Follow me, and I shall see that the usher gives you a seat up in front.
               I know you will find the way in here, and I have at last, thank God, found it
               myself!" </p>
            <p>Rosa wondered at this, but could ask no questions. They were entering the imposing
               building now, while throngs of well-dressed people, eyeing her curiously, were
               surging by. She was disappointed, for her past experience had convinced her that no
               well-dressed person but her one girl in blue, knew the way to the beautiful land. </p>
            <p>While she was considering the advisability of an immediate retreat, the policeman
               called to an usher: </p>
            <p>"Here, Dawson, are some friends of mine whom I want Dr. Fairfax to meet personally.
               Send a messenger for him at once. I know he will be willing to come; then give them
               good seats where they can both hear and see. Do just as I say, for these are my very
               special friends," he added, as the usher looked at him both quizzically and
               uncertainly. </p>
            <p>"And, Dawson, tell him, too, that I have found the way, praise the Lord!</p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="69" />"I must go now, and God take
               care of you, Rosa. You have taught me what you so want to know yourself. The old Book
               says that a little child shall lead them, and it is true." </p>
            <p>The usher hesitated somewhat to break the pastor's quiet half-hour which he had
               always spent with a few faithful workers before going into the pulpit, but seeing the
               tears beginning to roll down the sweet, sad face of the child, he sent the messenger
               post-haste. </p>
            <p>Very soon a tall, handsome man appeared.</p>
            <p>"Good morning, Mr. Dawson, and what may I do for you?" he pleasantly inquired. </p>
            <p>Something about his voice and kindly manner attracted Rosa immediately, and,
               characteristically impulsive, not waiting for Mr. Dawson's reply she ran up to the
               stranger's side and said: </p>
            <p>"Oh, please, mister, won't you tell me how to go? The policeman said you could.
               Grandpa and me want to go to the beautiful land, and mother's gone. Folks don't cough
               no more there, and Jesus paid all the fare, 'cause the pretty lady said so, and it
               don't cost nothing after you get there. Can you tell me the way?" </p>
            <p>The pastor in his surprise stood motionless for a moment, then astonished Mr. Dawson
               by lifting the little girl up in his arms and kissing her fondly. </p>
            <p>"Rosa," he said, "you are the straying lamb for <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="70" />whom Esther and I have been praying for
               weeks, and now God has sent you. By His help I shall teach you the way this very
               morning. </p>
            <p>"This is grandpa, is it not?" he added, grasping the old man cordially by the hand.
               "I am indeed very glad to see you. </p>
            <p>"Mr. Dawson, you are needed to seat the people. I shall escort these to a pew
               myself." </p>
            <p>The trio a few minutes later slowly passing down the aisle was certainly unusually
               striking. The pastor, with head erect and thoroughly conscious that many were
               displeased, was half supporting upon his strong right arm the shabbily-dressed and
               feeble man, while the child in ragged apparel he tenderly led by the hand. </p>
            <p>An observant eye might have noted various expressions upon the faces in the audience.
               Some evidently were disgusted that their popular pastor would so demean himself.
               Others were interested because of the oddity of the scene, still others amused, while
               here and there was one conversant with the language of the Master and who prayed
               God's blessing to abide upon all three. </p>
            <p>Belonging to the first-named class was Dr. Dale, wealthy, cautiously conservative
               always, aristocratic, exclusive in his circle of friends, and who wished also to be
               exclusive in his church relationship. The knowledge <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="71" />of his power over the majority of his
               acquaintances was a source of constant gratification to the proud man, but the fact
               that his pastor would not bow the knee to his wealth and position chafed him sorely.
               The events of this particular Sunday morning he took as only another personal insult. </p>
            <p>"Umph!" he grunted in deep displeasure, and reached over to pick up his hat
               preparatory to leaving. He could not countenance anything so ridiculously absurd. If
               the pastor's eccentricities continued to develop as they had in the last year, he
               would be compelled to seek another and more congenial church home, where form was
               more in evidence. </p>
            <p>Prim little Mrs. Dale, the one person in the world who could influence her austere
               husband, gently tapped him upon the arm and whispered: </p>
            <p>"Stay, my dear, and see what comes of it all. It is really quite unusual." </p>
            <p>"Well," he thought, "I'll stay to please her, and in the meantime take a nap." </p>
            <p>More to his discomfiture than ever, Dr. Fairfax had seated the strange pair directly
               across the aisle from him in the pew with Esther. </p>
            <p>Glancing over to note the effect upon her, Mr. Dale saw that she took the little girl
               up into her lap, bestowing upon her fond caresses. He looked long enough <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="72" />for Rosa's large brown eyes to meet his
               own, then with a great heart pang turned away. When had he ever seen so perfect a
               likeness to his own Margaret, his only and idolized darling, who had left his home
               the year before? Something seemed to be clutching at his heart most relentlessly,
               while a lump was filling his throat. Nervously and hastily lest his wife might see,
               he wiped from his brow the gathering perspiration. Persistently he endeavored to
               settle down for the nap, but with eyes either closed or open, all he could see was
               the child across the aisle. One moment he wished to fold her within his arms so
               strangely empty for twelve long months, and the next mentally upbraided her for so
               cruelly tearing open the one deep wound of his life. </p>
            <p>Presently he became aware that the voluntary had ceased, and that a restlessness was
               sweeping over the great audience. Arousing himself somewhat from his harrowing
               reveries, he looked at his watch and found that it was ten minutes past the time for
               the service to begin, and Dr. Fairfax had not yet entered the pulpit. </p>
            <p>While the people were wondering what the cause of the delay might be, he appeared. </p>
            <p>An unusual note of tenderness in the invocation prepared the auditors in some degree
               for what followed. </p>
            <p>"Brethren," he said, "it is recorded in Holy Writ that Jesus took a child and set it
               in the midst of <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="73" />them. Just as
               truly has He set in our midst today a child, and for this reason the whole order of
               service shall be changed. God helping me, I shall hide behind the cross, that the
               people may see Jesus only, and I shall present the way of salvation so simply that
               wayfaring men, though fools, shall not err therein. </p>
            <p>"We are living in a rationalistic age, when by many the God of miracles is denied;
               when the incarnation of the Son of God is considered a fable, having its counterpart
               in nearly all religions; when a belief in a literal hell and a literal heaven is
               becoming obsolete; when the atonement of our Lord Jesus Christ, making it possible to
               escape the one and gain the other, is held as a relic of superstition; when the
               verbal inspiration of the Bible is ridiculed; and when character-building is rapidly
               superseding the belief in the necessity of the new birth. </p>
            <p>"Perhaps I have not been sufficiently determined myself to know nothing among you
               save Jesus Christ and Him crucified, and have spoken too often upon popular themes.
               Today I shall not speak upon the subject announced, 'Applied Christianity the Remedy
               for Social Evils,' but," and he looked down upon Rosa to be sure that she understood,
               "'Heaven, or the Way to the Beautiful Land.' Preparatory to what I may say, I shall
               read the last two chapters of Revelation." </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="74" />"And I saw a new heaven and a
               new earth: for the first heaven and the first earth were passed away; and there was
               no more sea. </p>
            <p>"And I John saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven,
               prepared as a bride adorned for her husband. </p>
            <p>"And I heard a great voice out of heaven saying, Behold, the tabernacle of God is
               with men, and He will dwell with them, and they shall be His people, and God Himself
               shall be with them, and be their God. And God shall wipe away all tears from their
               eyes; and there shall be no more death, neither sorrow, nor crying, neither shall
               there be any more pain: for the former things are passed away. </p>
            <p>"And He that sat upon the throne said, Behold, I make all things new. And He said
               unto me, Write: for these words are true and faithful. And He said unto me, It is
               done. I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end. I will give unto him that is
               athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely. He that overcometh shall inherit
               all things; and I will be his God, and he shall be My son. But the fearful, and
               unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and
               idolaters, and all liars shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire
               and brimstone: which is the second death. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="75" />"And there came unto me one
               of the seven angels which had the seven vials full of the seven last plagues, and
               talked with me, saying, Come hither, I will show thee the bride, the Lamb's wife. </p>
            <p>"And he carried me away in the spirit to a great and high mountain, and showed me
               that great city, the holy Jerusalem, descending out of heaven from God, having the
               glory of God: and her light was like unto a stone most precious, even like a jasper
               stone, clear as crystal; and a wall great and high, and had twelve gates, and at the
               gates twelve angels, and names written thereon, which are the names of the twelve
               tribes of the children of Israel: on the east three gates; on the north three gates;
               on the south three gates; and on the west three gates. </p>
            <p>"And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and in them the names of the twelve
               apostles of the Lamb. </p>
            <p>"And he that talked with me had a golden reed to measure the city, and the gates
               thereof, and the wall thereof. And the city lieth foursquare, and the length is as
               large as the breadth * * * * </p>
            <p>"And the building of the wall of it was of jasper: and the city was pure gold, like
               unto clear glass. And the foundations of the wall of the city were garnished with all
               manner of precious stones * * * * And the <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator"
                  value="76" />twelve gates were twelve pearls; every several gate was of one
               pearl; and the street of the city was pure gold, as it were transparent glass. </p>
            <p>"And I saw no temple therein: for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the temple
               of it. And the city had no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine in it: for
               the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof. </p>
            <p>"And the nations of them which are saved shall walk in the light of it: and the kings
               of the earth do bring their glory and honor into it. And the gates of it shall not be
               shut at all by day: for there shall be no night there. And they shall bring the glory
               and honor of the nations into it. And there shall in no wise enter into it any thing
               that defileth, neither whatsoever worketh abomination, or maketh a lie: but they
               which are written in the Lamb's book of life. </p>
            <p>"And he showed me a pure river of water of life, clear as crystal, proceeding out of
               the throne of God and of the Lamb. </p>
            <p>"In the midst of the street of it, and on either side of the river, was there the
               tree of life, which bare twelve manner of fruits, and yielded her fruit every month:
               and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations. </p>
            <p>"And there shall be no more curse: but the throne of <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="77" /> God and of the Lamb shall be in it:
               and His servants shall serve Him: and they shall see His face; and His names shall be
               in their foreheads. And there shall be no night there; and they need no candle,
               neither light of the sun; for the Lord God giveth them light: and they shall reign
               for ever and ever * * * * </p>
            <p>"Blessed are they that do His commandments, that they may have right to the tree of
               life, and may enter in through the gates into the city." </p>
            <p>This incomparable description of the New Jerusalem, read in a finely modulated voice,
               had a marked effect upon the audience, though the reader was conscious of the
               presence of but three, Rosa, grandpa, and the Lord Jesus Himself. </p>
            <p>Dr. Dale was more disgusted than ever, or at least tried to be.</p>
            <p>"What unreasonable fanaticism!" he thought. "When men leave their homes and business
               to attend church, they want something practical, something acting as a stimulus in
               daily life. Being surrounded as we are on every hand by social evils, strife between
               capital and labor, and with anarchical tendencies becoming constantly more prevalent,
               we need something bearing directly upon these problems. There'll be time enough for
               these other things. Of course I believe <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator"
                  value="78" />in heaven, for Margaret is there, and when I die I want to go to
               her. </p>
            <p>"I wish Dr. Fairfax had left these vagrants where they belong. The child's face
               haunts me. Her eyes are almost as starry and full of expression as Margaret's. That's
               the queerest little old man I ever saw. I can't see how they happen to be here." </p>
            <p>And so his mind wandered restlessly on during the preliminary services.</p>
            <p>"Let all the people," announced the speaker, "join in singing that old hymn which
               some of us have not heard in years, 'The Home of the Soul.'" </p>
            <p>The great organ filled the vast auditorium with the strains of the melody, followed
               by a volume of sweetest song. Many were carried back to the scenes of their
               childhood, where, gathered around the family altar, were the dear ones long since
               singing in paradise. </p>
            <p>The strangers across the aisle again attracted Dr. Dale's attention. The old man was
               leaning forward with both hands resting upon his cane, his eyes were closed, and the
               tears were slowly trickling down the wrinkled face, while with a plaintive, quavery
               voice he was joining in the singing of his well-beloved song. </p>
            <p>At last it was time for the sermon, but the preacher, who by his eloquence and
               magnetic personality could <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="79"
                />sway thousands, felt as helpless as a little child to perform the duty before him. </p>
            <p>He announced his text: "Jesus saith unto him, I am the way" (John 14:6).</p>
            <p>The audience wondered why at that particular point he stopped apparently to offer a
               word of silent prayer. But then they could not see the expression of hope flash
               across the face of the child, nor the old man lean still a little farther forward
               that he might catch every word. </p>
            <p>"Rosa," whispered grandpa, "didn't I tell you if we'd go to a meetin' house with the
               steeple a-p'intin' straight up, we'd find the way? Yes, yes, that's it, it surely is,
               Rosa, and it's all a-beginnin' to come back. Jesus is the way, Jesus is the way! I
               wonder I ain't thought of it before." </p>
            <p>The sermon which followed, simple in every detail, began by calling attention to the
               marvelously beautiful description of the heavenly land as contained in the Scripture
               previously read. </p>
            <p>"There are representatives here today of many classes and conditions of society,"
               said the speaker, "the high and the low, the rich and the poor, the learned and the
               ignorant; but there is no eye that has not shed bitter tears, no life unacquainted
               with death, sorrow, crying, or pain. Thank God for that glad coming day <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="80" />when He will wipe away all tears, when
               there shall be no more death, neither sorrow, nor crying, nor pain; for these things
               shall have passed away!" </p>
            <p>He spoke of the glimpse the Scripture gives of the city itself, the New Jerusalem,
               with its walls and gates. "There is no language of earth by which its glories can be
               fully described," he continued; "where our idea of beauty leaves off, there heaven
               begins! Even its foundations are made of the rarest jewels we know. </p>
            <p>"But heaven's happiness consists not in mere outward things. God is there, and the
               Lamb! In God's presence is fulness of joy, and at His right hand are to be found the
               truest pleasures for evermore. There the redeemed out of every nation shall serve
               Him, and they shall see His face with no veil of time or sense between. </p>
            <p>"This holy city will never be marred by the entering in of anything that defileth,
               but only those whose names are written in the Lamb's book of life shall behold and
               enjoy its splendor and happiness. </p>
            <p>"I think I hear some poor soul say: 'Then there is no hope for me!'</p>
            <p>"Yes, there is hope!</p>
            <p>"'But I have sinned!'</p>
            <p>"That is true. All have sinned, and come short of the glory of God. There is none
               righteous, no, not one. We are by nature and practice strangers to God, <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="81" />even the new-born babe having wrapped
               up within its tiny bosom a sinful heritage and bias. And the soul that sinneth shall
               die. But sin can be put away, and its dreadful penalty escaped. Shall I not tell you
               how? </p>
            <p>"It is by the love and grace of our heavenly Father that we can be justified freely
               through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus. God loved us in our sin and
               rebellion, and sent His only-begotten Son to bring earth's inhabitants back to
               Himself, that they might share the joys of the heavenly home. Ere He came to earth,
               an angel of the Lord appeared and said His name should be called Jesus, for He should
               save His people from their sins. When at length He was born, the angel appeared to
               the wondering shepherds on the hillside near Bethlehem, and said: 'Behold, I bring
               you good tidings of great joy, which shall be to all people: for unto you is born
               this day a Saviour.' He came to seek and save the lost. For thirty years He lived a
               secluded but holy life at Nazareth. Then for three years He went about doing good,
               working marvelous miracles and saying wonderful words. At length they took Him, and
               crucified Him on Calvary! 'Behold,' John had said, 'the Lamb of God that taketh away
               the sin of the world!' Do you not see how it is? Christ died—not for His own sins,
               for He was holy, harmless, undefiled, but for your sins and mine. He bore our
                  <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="82" />sins in His body on the
               cross. Believe on Him, and you are saved! </p>
            <p>"Yes, childlike trust in the Lord Jesus Christ as your Saviour gives your soul peace
               with God and makes your entrance into the house of many mansions sure! He went back
               to prepare a place for us who believe on Him, and promised to come again and receive
               us unto Himself, that where He is, there we may be also. Jesus Himself is the way
               home!" </p>
            <p>So clearly did he explain the plan of salvation that Rosa began to grasp the truth.
               All the pent-up love of her ardent nature she began to bestow upon Jesus, and in the
               joy of this new experience forgot her crushing sorrow. </p>
            <p>The sermon closed by another extended reference to heaven, with special emphasis upon
               the fact of its being real, and not simply a state of blissful being, as many profess
               to believe, and with an appeal to the skeptical to take Jesus at His word. </p>
            <p>"He said, 'I go to prepare a place for you.' Is it not His positive statement
               sufficient? Has He ever proved untrue to His promises concerning this life? Has He
               ever turned a deaf ear to the penitent sinner's prayer? Has He ever refused to speak
               the word of comfort to the heart breaking beneath its load? Has He ever called one to
               some particular service in His vineyard <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator"
                  value="83" />without supplying the needed strength? Has He ever forgotten to
               pour forth His abundant and sustaining grace upon the trusting soul about the pass
               through the dark, mysterious valley of death? And would He say that He was going to
               prepare a place for us, that where He is there we may be also, meaning only that He
               was going to prepare a state of glorified— nothingness? Impossible! It is an insult
               to our Lord. </p>
            <p>"He who left the glory-circled throne for thirty-three years of wandering in this
               world, for rejection by those whom He came to save, for Gethsemane and for Calvary,
               will hold up no false hope to lure onward those who love Him. </p>
            <p>"He who created this beautiful world, inhabited by fallen sinful beings, will not
               forget to provide a home for His own who have washed their robes and made them white
               in the blood of the Lamb. </p>
            <p>"Yes, heaven is a place, where the power of infinity itself is exhausted in the
               beautifying thereof! No sin, no sickness, no sorrow will ever pass through those
               gates of pearl. The saints of all ages are there, our loved ones whom we have lost a
               while are there, and above all our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ! </p>
            <p>"Ah, if Satan has deluded you into a state of unbelief now, the time is coming when
               you will believe! Some day with unwilling feet you must part from your <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="84" /> Lord forever to spend eternity in
               hell; or with hosannas and shouts of victory upon your lips, you will pass into the
               presence of Him who sits upon the throne, to praise Him and serve Him forever and
               ever!" </p>
            <p>At the conclusion of the service, Dr. and Mrs. Dale left without waiting to speak to
               the pastor. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Dale, however, stopped ostensibly to greet Esther, but in reality to look more
               closely at the child who had attracted her quite as much as her husband. </p>
            <p>The doctor's perturbed state did not admit of his speaking to any one. He longed for
               Margaret, and both loved and hated the little waif who unconsciously had so
               remarkably altered the affairs of the whole morning. He had endeavored not to listen
               to the sermon, "fit only for children, and not for men possessed of a logical turn of
               mind," he said to himself; but the more he tried, with the greater persistency did
               the ringing sentences surge through his aching brain. </p>
            <p>"Well!" he exclaimed to his wife as soon as they were seated in their carriage, "Dr.
               Fairfax is a narrow-minded extremist, a fanatic. What right had he to bring those
               street wanderers into the church this morning? The place for them is down at the
               mission. Do I not give liberally toward its support? To be sure, such as they need
               the Gospel, but I want them to stay where they belong to get it." </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="85" />"But, my dear," placidly
               remonstrated his wife, "there may be qualifying circumstances connected with all this
               which we do not understand." </p>
            <p>"Possibly, but scarcely probable anything to warrant such an unheard-of innovation!
               The place for them is down at the mission, I say. </p>
            <p>"And that sermon, if such it may be called! I thought I was at a funeral. There were
               hundreds of men there, who like myself went for something helpful and practical. Who
               cares to discuss the heavenly city when our city down here is in the throes of a
               strike, threatening to paralyze business for weeks and months to come, and meaning
               the loss of millions of dollars, both directly and indirectly?" </p>
            <p>"I know, dear, but the Father's omnipotent hand of love will bring everything out
               right some day. He has promised, and His promises never fail. Is it not restful, and
               does it not make one more brave for the conflict, to know that there is an abiding
               city, at whose portals we leave earth's sorrows and perplexities?" </p>
            <p>"Yes, wife, I know, but we are living now upon this mundane sphere, and naturally our
               interests center here. A belief in heaven does not straighten out affairs on earth,
               nor make the burdens any the lighter to bear." </p>
            <p>"I do not know about that, since Margaret has gone. If I did not believe what Dr.
               Fairfax said this morning, <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="86" />my
               burden, at least, would be much heavier and harder to bear. It does help to know that
               she is safe, and that I shall join her myself some day." </p>
            <p>"Oh, well, yes, of course, but then it's different when it comes to Margaret!" </p>
            <p>For several minutes they rode in silence, when the doctor said:</p>
            <p>"Wife, did you see that child's eyes?"</p>
            <p>"Yes, I saw them."</p>
            <p>"I wish—well, we are home now! Let me assist you from the carriage."</p>
            <p>In the meantime, grandpa and Rosa were having an experience very novel to them. </p>
            <p>Upon discovering grandpa's weak condition, a carriage had been ordered, the first one
               in which they had ever ridden. Esther was quietly explaining to Rosa more of Jesus
               and His love for the children, while her receptive little soul was eagerly taking it
               all in. </p>
            <p>"Then," she said, "I can't go to the beautiful land till He sends for me! I do wish
               He would send soon." </p>
            <p>"No, but He surely will send some day, Rosa, and perhaps He wants you to teach others
               how to get there." </p>
            <p>"If He does, then I'm willing to stay, 'cause so many don't know."</p>
            <p>In her broken childish way, Rosa told of the many <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="87" />and varied experiences befalling her
               and grandpa since mother moved. </p>
            <p>Esther and her father were greatly touched by the pathos of the narrative, but what
               left the deepest impression was that in her eager quest she could find no one for so
               long to help her. </p>
            <p>There in the privacy of their carriage they gave themselves anew to the work of the
               Lord, pledging never again to let a known opportunity to speak to a needy soul pass
               by. </p>
            <p>Grandpa, like a tired child, was resting his head upon the shoulder of his new friend
               during the drive, and it was evident that he was very ill. The fever was returning,
               the mind partially wandering, but the soul rejoicing in the light of that land which
               he so soon was to enter. </p>
            <p>"Ah, Rosa," he murmured over and over, "I told you so. Jesus is the way, Jesus is the
               way! I'm mighty glad it's all come back, but Tom he said 'twould, and I think he'
               a-comin' now to git me." </p>
            <p>Upon their arrival home, with tender hands the weary old man was put to bed, while
               Esther took charge of Rosa, clothing her in more suitable garments, and talking
               simply of the Shepherd who seeks the wandering lambs. </p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="88" />
            <h>VII. VICTORY!</h>
            <p>The deserted rooms on Burton street suddenly became the scene of great activity early
               Monday afternoon. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Gray's supersensitive conscience would not admit of her neglecting her charges,
               so in consequence her visit was made a few hours shorter than first planned. </p>
            <p>The fire was out, and no trace could she find of Rosa and grandpa. She "hollered till
               her throat was sore," looked in every reasonable—and unreasonable—corner, searched up
               and down the hall, inquired of her neighbors, visited the corner grocery, but all to
               no avail. </p>
            <p>"Land sakes!" over and over she repeated to a group of interested spectators, "I
               might a-know'd better'n to have gone off and left them. This is jest my luck,
                  <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="89" />anyhow. The first time
               I've been away in five years, then have this happen. I'm jest real provoked, and I
               don't think a body could blame me, either. But it all comes of me bein' so obligin'.
               If it wuzn't fer my tender heart, I'd never kep' Tom's father, nor took Mis'
               Browning's young one, then I could come and go as I pleased and not be pestered this
               way. There ain't many that'd do fer others what I do, and I never git no thanks fer
               it, neither. If I hadn't had father to board all these years, I might have somethin'
               laid up fer a rainy day, and there ain't nobody but what'll say I'm industrious and
               savin'. </p>
            <p>"But I can't think where they'd go, nor what I can do. It seems like somebody'd seen
               them. I'll fix them when they git back, so as they'll never do it ag'in. It looks
               like they'd been gone fer some time, and I do b'lieve they've been into the tea and
               stove blackin'. I never thought about blackin', who would? but I told them not to
               touch that tea, fer I couldn't afford it. They'll be sorry, they will, when I git
               hold of them. </p>
            <p>"Here you, Billy Bruce!" she vociferously called, catching sight of that youth
               running down the stairs three steps at a time; "come right back here at fast as you
               can, and tell me what you know about Rosa and grandpa. You're always under foot
               a-knowin' what's a-goin' on, so I 'spose if anybody seen them you did." </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="90" />Billy feared Mrs. Gray more
               than he did the judge or policeman—that is, at close range; but when occupying the
               vantage-ground, as at the present, he delighted in revolt. </p>
            <p>"I didn't either see them," he shouted back, "and don't know nothin' about them, only
               I'd run off, too, if I wuz them." </p>
            <p>At this the greatly abused and misunderstood woman picked up a piece of coal to hurl
               at the rapidly retreating young rebel, when, to her astonishment, she saw coming up
               the steps the transformed Rosa with Esther! </p>
            <p>"You'd better look out, Rosa," confidently explained Billy, "she's awful mad, and you
               may git that lickin' yet, you said she'd been a-promisin'." </p>
            <p>Rosa shrank in terror, her face growing pale and twitching nervously, while an
               inclination to run away with her barbarous but devoted champion took possession of
               her. </p>
            <p>"Never mind, dear," whispered Esther reassuringly, "she will do you no harm while I
               am with you. You need not be at all afraid." </p>
            <p>Upon looking into the fearless blue eyes of Esther, Mrs. Gray suddenly determined to
               change her plan of attack. </p>
            <p>"Land sakes, Rosa! I've been that worried about you and father, the dear old
               soul,—where is he? and where <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="91"
                />have you been, and where did you git them pretty clothes? Why didn't you tell me
               you wanted to go on a visit, and what made you stay so long? Of course it wuz awful
               lonesome here without me, so I won't blame you much, but children'd ought to tell." </p>
            <p>Not giving the child an opportunity to answer, a volley of interrogations and
               information was turned upon Esther. </p>
            <p>"What's your name? Esther Fairfax, is it? well, now that's a real pretty name, but do
               come right in and set down. Things is in a muss, fer I've been gone, and children
               don't amount to much fer work, 'specially when they ain't been raised right. I ain't
               had her long, you know, or she'd be different. Her ma wuz awful queer and silly about
               her. But where did you find her? You wuz real thoughtful to bring her back to me, so
               as I wouldn't worry any longer'n necessary. I 'spose you found her clothes in bad
               shape. Her ma's been dead now a while, and didn't keep things up as well as she might
               anyhow, I thought, fer some time. She wuz one of them women that gives up easy, but
               that's somethin' I never do. I've been a-layin' out to show Rosa how to sew. She's
               plenty old enough, and I ain't got no time to do it myself. But then I never did
               b'lieve in bringin' them up lazy. There's a lot in gittin' them started right. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="92" />"And where on earth's the old
               man? I can't think how you found them. Seems like a month since I seen him, but then
               I have more attachment and affection than most folks, or I wouldn't a been so
               flustered. I hope he's acted with some sense, so as I won't have to be mortified." </p>
            <p>Endeavoring to impress her guest favorably, Mrs. Gray, while talking, was
               energetically moving about the room, making some pretense toward bringing order out
               of confusion. </p>
            <p>"That grease spot down there on the floor by the stove does really worry me a heap,
               and I'd really ought to—" </p>
            <p>At this Rosa cast a glance at the whip still reposing above the door, and tightened
               her clasp upon Esther's hand. </p>
            <p>"Father's awful childish, and I have to treat him jest like a child, too, or I
               couldn't git on with him no how. I've kep' him now, well, let me see: it's a-goin' on
               six years since Tom got killed, and I've been a-supportin' him ever since, and no
               tellin' how much longer he'll live. If it wuzn't fer my kind heart, I'd tell him he'd
               have to leave. I've thought of it some lately, but then s'pose I never will. Then
               when Mis' Browning died, of course she wanted me to raise Rosa. It's a good thing she
               did die fer now Rosa'll learn to do somethin' <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="93" /> more'n jest to be kissed and cried
               over. I used to git that provoked at her ma fer actin' so silly. I didn't say she
               could stay here only till spring. Of course she come in real handy like when father
               didn't mind and I twisted my ankle, but then it's sech a bother to raise a child.
               When she ain't no more use to me, I don't know how it'll be then." </p>
            <p>During this recital, Esther's face was a study. She had visited much among the poor
               with her father, but never before had she come into contact with quite so unusual a
               character as Mrs. Gray. Finding that her only opportunity to state her errand was to
               interrupt the loquacious speaker, she determined to wait no longer. </p>
            <p>"Mrs. Gray, I have come to tell you that you will never again be troubled by grandpa
               or Rosa. Grandpa is in my home, and the physician says that he can live but a few
               hours longer. He has had a raging fever, but that has left now; he is entirely
               rational and wishes to see you before the Master calls. </p>
            <p>"My carriage is waiting. There is no time to lose. Put on your wraps and come
               immediately." </p>
            <p>So surprised was Mrs. Gray that for the instant an almost unprecedented thing
               occurred: she could think of nothing to say. But endeavoring to gain her normal
               poise, she turned upon Rosa. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="94" />"Well, you heard what the
               lady said! Father, the dear old soul, of course he wants to see me before he dies,
               after all I've done fer him; but how lonely it'll be without him! Seems like I can
               see him a-settin' over there in his chair now, a-lookin' out of the winder, like he
               did 'most all day sometimes." </p>
            <p>At this appropriate juncture, she made a fruitless effort to shed a few tears, but,
               to be charitable, the deepest sorrow cannot find expression in tears. </p>
            <p>"You can stay here, Rosa, and have supper ready when I git back, and make me some
               tea; I'll need it to settle my nerves. Take them fine clothes off, too, before you
               spoil 'em. I want you to learn to be savin', like I've always been. And give that
               grease spot another scrubbin', and go to the corner grocery and git—" </p>
            <p>"No, Mrs. Gray," vehemently interposed Esther, "did I not tell you that Rosa is never
               going to live with you again? You are about to realize your dream of liberty, for
               which without a doubt you are duly grateful. You seem to feel that both grandpa and
               Rosa have been intolerable burdens." </p>
            <p>Esther was the repetition of her father, and when the case demanded could be firm and
               commandingly dignified. </p>
            <p>Again Mrs. Gray was speechless. For so long she <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="95" />had been absolute monarch in her small
               realm, with none daring to question or to rise in rebellion, that it was a revelation
               to find in a young woman like Esther an opposite and stronger force with which to
               reckon. </p>
            <p>For the first time in her life she was completely conquered, and without another word
               marched solemnly down to the carriage. </p>
            <p>"This is an opportunity," thought Esther, "and may I be directed in all I say." </p>
            <p>Not wishing this woman possessed of a hard heart and a shriveled soul to stand in awe
               of her any longer, a few kind and ordinary remarks soon accomplished the desired end. </p>
            <p>"Well, Miss Esther, you ain't told me how it's all come about. I can't fer the life
               of me think, and it all seems so strange. I jest can't git it through my head that
               father's a-goin' to die. Are you real sure of it? Mebbe there's a mistake." </p>
            <p>"No, Mrs. Gray, there is no mistake. In a few hours he will be safe forever in the
               better land." </p>
            <p>Esther's power of narration was well developed. Going into the minute details, she
               simply told the whole story, while Mrs. Gray attentively listened without an
               interruption. There were indications that the hitherto impregnable fortress of this
               untutored woman's heart was beginning to totter. But is there after <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="96" />all in this great world a heart so
               loveless, so blackened by sin, or so narrowed by its own selfish domain, as to be
               entirely invincible? Cannot the love emanating from Christ Himself, flowing through
               the channel of a surrendered life, leave its impress where all else fails? </p>
            <p>Esther's observant eye noted the change, then skilfully she began speaking of the
               Lord as a personal Saviour. </p>
            <p>Presently tears began rolling down the hardened cheeks, causing the young messenger
               to feel that victory was almost certain. </p>
            <p>Upon reaching the Fairfax home, Mrs. Gray was ushered into a room, which to her
               seemed magnificent. </p>
            <p>Grandpa was lying upon an immaculate bed, while everything surrounding him was far
               more indicative of loving thoughtfulness than of luxury. In his hand he clasped a
               beautiful rose, because during his rational moments he so often spoke of the "pretty
               roses a-growin' by the brook down in the lane." The rose was presented by none other
               than Dr. Dale, not—so he assured himself—that he was in the least sympathetic with
               the Fairfaxes in their eccentric freak. It was simply for the good of the patient
               that all small whims be humored. </p>
            <p>Upon a nearby table was Esther's violin. During the long hours of the preceding
               night, when the burning <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="97" />fever
               produced a great restlessness in the weary sufferer, nothing soothed him but the low,
               sweet strains of music. </p>
            <p>Now he was calm, and for the first time since Tom died clothed in his right mind. </p>
            <p>"Sary, how be you?" he feebly asked, as she slowly walked up to his side. "I'm so
               glad you've come, fer it's all straightened out now, and I want to thank you afore I
               go fer all you've done fer me. And may somebody take care of you real kind when you
               git old and can't work no more. I've been a big bother, Sary. You've had a good deal
               to put up with since Tom died, but you've been mighty kind. You've always give me
               enough to eat, and kep' me warm, and you've had to work awful hard to do it. I thank
               you, Sary, and may God bless you! But I do want you to find Jesus, the way to the
               beautiful land. You won't have it so hard there. He's paid for everything, and it's
               free fer the askin'." </p>
            <p>"Oh, father," she said, dropping upon her knees and weeping bitterly for the first
               time in many years, "you ain't got nothin' to thank me fer. I've never seen till jest
               this minute how awful mean I've been. You did your very best to please me, and the
               harder you tried, the more I scolded. I wish I'd been better to you. No, you ain't
               got nothin' at all to thank me fer, and I'll <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator"
                  value="98" />miss you so! I don't know why I've never seen it before, and you've
               always been so good. I'll never git over feelin' mean about it, no, I never will, oh
               dear, dear!" </p>
            <p>"There, there, Sary, don't cry! It's all right now."</p>
            <p>Tenderly he stroked the hand which many times had been raised threateningly against
               him, and tried to soothe the thoroughly conscience-striken woman. </p>
            <p>"Sary, I do want you to find Jesus. It's so mighty sweet to know Him, and He'll help
               you over all the hard places,—He says He will; and He always carries the heavy end of
               the load, too." </p>
            <p>"I'm too wicked and mean, father. He wouldn't have me," she sobbed, "but I wish He
               would; I need Him bad, and want help." </p>
            <p>"Mrs. Gray,"—it was the minister who spoke and who had been a silent witness of the
               pathetic scene,—"Jesus died to save you." </p>
            <p>"I wish I knew it," she moaned, "but I'm too mean. I'm the biggest sinner in the
               world to treat father and Rosa the way I have." </p>
            <p>"If you are the biggest sinner in the world, then I know that Jesus died to save you.
               Listen to His word: 'This is a faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptation, that
               Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners; of whom I am chief.' You consider
               yourself the chief of sinners, do you?" </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="99" />"Yes, I do; I know I am." </p>
            <p>"Who came to save the chief of sinners?"</p>
            <p>"Why, the verse says Christ Jesus did."</p>
            <p>"Yes, Mrs. Gray, that is true. Then whom did Jesus Christ come to save?"</p>
            <p>"Oh, He came to save me, He came to save me! How could He ever do it?"</p>
            <p>"Just because God so loved the world, that He gave His only begotten Son, that
               whosoever believeth in Him should not perish, but have everlasting life. Do you
               believe it?" </p>
            <p>"Yes, how can I help it, when He done all that?"</p>
            <p>"Then if you believe in Him, what have you?"</p>
            <p>"Everlasting life! Everlasting life!" Dreamily, yet joyously, she repeated the words
               many times, trying to comprehend their fathomless depths. </p>
            <p>"But," she anxiously asked, "what about my sins? You don't know how mean I've been." </p>
            <p>"'And their sins and iniquities will I remember no more.'"</p>
            <p>"Oh, thank God, thank God! He's give me everlasting life, and won't remember my sins.
               I want to begin all over now, and do somethin' fer Him before I die." </p>
            <p>In broken petitions she poured forth her heart in prayer to God, while at the same
               moment angelic songs <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="100" />were
               started anew around the throne above. Another soul was born again. </p>
            <p>Is there less rejoicing over there when the soul saved chances to be the tenant of a
               roughly-hewn temple? Ah no, for it required the shedding of just the same precious
               blood as for the souls of earth's greatest and noblest! </p>
            <p>An expression of unspeakable peace lighted up grandpa's happy face, as he murmured: </p>
            <p>"Oh, Sary, I'm so glad, so mighty glad! Now I'll tell Tom you're a-comin', and we'll
               both be a-watchin' fer you. Won't we be happy when we all git safe home? Goodby,
               Sary! You've always been a good woman, yes, a very good woman, and now Jesus will
               take care of you. Goodby, till we meet ag'in!" </p>
            <p>The effort of speaking seemed to exhaust him perceptably, and he sank off into a deep
               sleep. </p>
            <p>It was evident that the end was near, and hastily Dr. Dale was summoned. Upon
               examining his patient, he found that in a few minutes, or perhaps a half an hour at
               the most, all would be over. </p>
            <p>Silently they watched him. Rosa understood better now than she did a few weeks before
               what the "moving" meant. She knew that she would be lonely without grandpa, her one
               comforter through many a dark and dreary hour, and the tears began to gather. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="101" />At this Dr. Dale became
               restless. Just to avoid a scene, he took the little girl up into his arms, wiping
               away the tears and whispering words of comfort. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Gray sat nearest the dying man, gently smoothing back the snowy locks from his
               forehead. His breath was growing shorter and shorter, but there was no struggle.
               Suddenly his eyes opened, and with a smile of recognition he greeted each one. </p>
            <p>"Oh," he faintly whispered, "Jesus is the way, Jesus is the way! Sing to me my song,
               won't you, please?" </p>
            <p>With difficulty Esther and her father complied with the request, while the doctor
               walked nervously up and down the room with Rosa still in his arms. </p>
            <d:poem>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"Oh, how sweet it will be in that beautiful land, </l>

                  <l>So free from all sorrow and pain, </l>

                  <l>With songs on our lips and with harps in our hands, </l>

                  <l>To meet one another again!" </l>

               </d:stanza>
            </d:poem>
            <p>As the words of the last verse died away, the soul took its flight to rejoice forever
               in the presence of the King. </p>
            <p>"O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory? Thanks be to God which
               giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ." </p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="102" />
            <h>VIII. DUST TO DUST.</h>
            <p>The events of Sunday morning had occasioned much comment upon the part of Dr.
               Fairfax's parishioners. </p>
            <p>The majority, after taking time for consideration, approved, and became intensely
               interested to know the outcome of the strange proceeding. During the few hours of
               grandpa's illness many messengers called to learn the latest news, and it cheered the
               pastor's heart to find that after all he was far from being alone in his love for
               God's neglected poor. </p>
            <p>He had planned a quiet funeral, and was arranging to that effect when requests from
               all sides began pouring in that it might be held in the church. </p>
            <p>"It is a signal opportunity, father," Esther had said when consulted, so a public
               funeral was soon announced <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="103"
                />together with another innovation. Instead of the customary floral offerings, it
               was suggested that the people bring gifts of money to place upon the casket, to be
               used in the forwarding of city mission work. </p>
            <p>At the hour appointed, the small procession wended its way to the church. </p>
            <p>Dr. Dale had found it advisable for himself and wife to join the funeral party. It
               was natural that Esther should look after Mrs. Gray, who never before had been in so
               fine a building, and it would be awkward for her to have charge of Rosa as well. Then
               really the child was very nervous and might suddenly need professional attention. All
               things considered, there was no alternative: he must keep her with him. </p>
            <p>Both curiosity and genuine interest attracted a great crowd, causing the pastor once
               more to feel his need of hiding behind the cross, that the people might behold Jesus
               only. </p>
            <p>In all his wide and varied experience, this funeral pre-eminently was the most
               unique. Conventionality was laid aside. There was no sermon, but the story of the
               last few days of the victor's life was told so graphically that the audience was held
               in almost breathless silence. </p>
            <p>"Brethren," said the speaker in closing, "how must we appear in the sight of God, who
               loved us to the extent <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="104" />of
               giving His only Son to die for our sins, when it is possible for one to live long,
               weary years in our midst with none to tell him of Jesus? Can we expect ever to hear
               from His lips the welcome plaudit, 'Well done!' when we are no more zealous than this
               for the souls whom He came to save? </p>
            <p>"I fear that many who profess to love Him will fall far short of the 'abundant
               entrance,' and will stand ashamed before Him at His appearing. </p>
            <p>"Can it be true that we are selfish to the extent of being satisfied simply with our
               own salvation, when His heart of infinite love and compassion is yearning with
               unfathomable tenderness over the lost? </p>
            <p>"We have the opportunity now which angels may well covet, that of leading souls to
               Christ. This priceless privilege is intrusted to us only for the one brief moment of
               our earthly existence, and how we should prize it above all things else! </p>
            <p>"Consider the fact that one million of years hence, yea, millions of millions of
               years, your happiness and capacity for enjoying Christ and heaven depend upon the
               manner of your spending this present vapor called life. When eventually we are
               ushered through the gates of the Eternal City, it will then be forever too late for
               this one blood-purchased pleasure of telling salvation's story to the lost. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="105" />"It seems a paradox that it
               is possible for one to be a Christian without having a consuming passion for souls.
               But in reality the whole matter centers not upon our love for those around us, but
               upon our love for the Lord Jesus Himself. When we are in unbroken fellowship with
               Christ, the natural result is love for those so dear to Him. 'The love of Jesus is
               not an absorbing, but a radiating love. The more we love Him, the more shall we most
               certainly love others.' Each new revelation of Himself graciously granted unto His
               followers only draws us the nearer to Him, the fountain of eternal love, where we
               drink to our fill and are imbued with an all-consuming desire to carry the
               life-giving water unto others. </p>
            <p>"Nor can we gaze long at the cross, at the cruelly mutilated brow of our Saviour, at
               His body torn and bruised by the merciless scourging, at the five bleeding wounds,
               nor can we listen to the cry of His broken heart, 'My God, My God, why hast Thou
               forsaken Me?' without being melted with love and filled with a holy zeal to serve Him
               every moment of our lives. One real view of the cross changes all. The things of this
               life, where we shall be located and how we shall be situated, will have no more
               effect upon us, if only we may glorify Him. </p>
            <p>"Many have taken the first step, giving into His <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="106" />keeping their souls for eternity, but
               will you not now, while beholding Him hanging on yonder cross for you, give Him your
               lives as well? The only life worth the living is the surrendered life. Time is
               uncertain, eternity sure. Now and only now may we prove to Him our love, and know the
               fellowship of His sufferings. </p>
            <p>"I ask every Christian here today, who is willing henceforth to yield his life, his
               time, his all, unconditionally into the hands of the Master and to go forth seeking
               those who need help, to arise." </p>
            <p>The speaker, though pale from emotion, calmly folded his arms and looked over the
               audience to see what the result might be. </p>
            <p>He knew that the crisis in the life of his church had arrived, and should the King
               have the victory, or no? </p>
            <p>For a moment there was not a stir. Then the preacher himself could scarcely believe
               what he saw. </p>
            <p>Dr. Dale, still holding Rosa in his arms, slowly arose, love and determination being
               depicted upon the hitherto cold and dignified countenance. The effect was pronounced.
               Soon hundreds were upon their feet, while some one started the song: </p>
            <d:poem>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"I gave My life for thee, </l>

                  <l>My precious blood I shed </l>

                  <l>That thou might'st ransomed be </l>

               </d:stanza>

               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="107" />
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>And quickened from the dead; </l>

                  <l>I gave My life for thee: </l>

                  <l>What hast thou done for Me? </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"My Father's house of light, </l>

                  <l>My glory-circled throne, </l>

                  <l>I left for earthly night, </l>

                  <l>For wanderings sad and lone; </l>

                  <l>I left it all for thee: </l>

                  <l>Hast thou left aught for Me? </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"I suffered much for thee, </l>

                  <l>More than thy tongue can tell, </l>

                  <l>Of bitterest agony, </l>

                  <l>To rescue thee from hell; </l>

                  <l>I've borne it all for thee: </l>

                  <l>What hast thou borne for Me? </l>

               </d:stanza>
               <d:stanza>

                  <l>"And I have brought to thee, </l>

                  <l>Down from my home above, </l>

                  <l>Salvation full and free, </l>

                  <l>My pardon and My love; </l>

                  <l>I bring rich gifts to thee: </l>

                  <l>What hast thou brought to Me?" </l>

               </d:stanza>
            </d:poem>
            <p>At the conclusion of the song the pastor led in a consecration prayer, knowing that
               in many the bonds of worldliness were forever snapped asunder, and that henceforth
               the victorious, overcoming life would be theirs, making themselves heirs of the
               promise: "To him that overcometh will I grant to sit with Me in My <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="108" />throne, even as I also overcame, and
               am set down with My Father in His throne." </p>
            <p>After a few moments of silence, the quartette softly sang "The Home of the Soul,"
               while a vast procession slowly marched before the casket, placing upon it gifts of
               silver, gold and bank notes all in one great heap. </p>
            <p>At last all that was earthly of him whose simple life and final victory had proven so
               powerful a sermon, was tenderly carried out and laid to rest in a beautiful lot
               purchased by Dr. Dale, while the setting sun was painting the western sky with almost
               heavenly glory. </p>
            <p>"God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to confound the wise; and God hath
               chosen the weak things of the world to confound the things which are mighty." </p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="109" />
            <h>IX. "A LITTLE CHILD SHALL LEAD THEM."</h>
            <p>The day was over.</p>
            <p>Esther and her father, possessed of a calm, holy joy deeper than ever before, were
               seated in his study, while with them were Dr. and Mrs. Dale, Rosa and Mrs. Gray. </p>
            <p>Esther had been undergoing a struggle, for it would be hard to give Rosa up. She had
               planned to keep her as her own little sister, to educate her, to train her in things
               both temporal and spiritual, and to guard her till she should develop into a pure,
               strong, noble woman. </p>
            <p>Now she felt that it must be otherwise, for evidently God had so determined. Knowing
               that His will always would be her deliberate choice, could she see the <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="110" />end from the beginning as He can, she
               was growing positively happy at this unexpected turn of events. It was a part of her
               religion not to be simply passively submissive to His will, but in it always to
               rejoice. The psalmist's declaration, "I delight to do Thy will, O my God," was the
               expression of her heart's desire. </p>
            <p>Mrs. Dale, though with an eye upon the child, was quietly talking to Mrs. Gray of the
               privileges and duties befalling the Christian. </p>
            <p>Dr. Dale was clasping Rosa closely to his breast, while now and then a tear dropped
               upon her curly head. </p>
            <p>"Pastor," he said after a long interval of silence, "the battle has raged fiercely
               since Sunday morning, but thanks be to God, He has given me the strength with which
               to gain the victory. </p>
            <p>"You know how selfish I have been, how taken up with the affairs of this world and
               the amassing of riches. For many years I have had no vital interest in other things.
               I have prided myself upon my uprightness and morality, considering that I was a
               worthy example for any to follow, and a decidedly successful man. Now the fallacy of
               my position I see, and realize that the best part of my life has been wasted—more
               than wasted! </p>
            <p>"When you walked down the aisle with Rosa and <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="111" />grandpa, Satan made upon me a
               relentless onslaught. It seemed that there were two mighty and opposing forces
               within, each struggling for the supremacy. I did not yield entirely to the right till
               this afternoon, for I have gloried in my reputation of being influenced by no one. </p>
            <p>"For years I have not been satisfied, knowing myself to be slipping farther and
               farther away from God. I have longed for the joy of my first love, but He could not
               take me back with my hands so tenaciously holding to the things of this world. </p>
            <p>"Today the tempter told me that there would be no use in my surrendering, for I would
               not prove true, and anyhow that it was only a matter of excitement and not of firm
               conviction. I fully realize that I have no power in myself, and that the first moment
               I look away from Christ I shall fall. I am resting on the promise that He is able to
               keep me from falling and to present me faultless before the presence of His glory
               with exceeding joy. </p>
            <p>"Your message Sunday and your message today burned deeply into my soul, but it is
               this little girl whom God was pleased to use in the breaking of my stony, icy heart.
               I wish to take her as my own daughter, knowing that she will lead me still closer to
               the Lord she loves so well. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="112" />"Rosa," he asked tenderly,
               "are you willing to be my little girl instead of my Margaret whom God has taken to
               Himself?" </p>
            <p>For her answer she slipped her arms about his neck and kissed him, while Mrs. Dale
               smiled through her tears upon the happy pair. </p>
            <p>"My brother, may God bless you and keep you," fervently responded the pastor,
               "leading you from victory up into victory. </p>
            <p>"You are not the only one to be filled with gratitude for having been brought under
               the influence of this child. I too view life differently, seeing more clearly than
               ever the duty, nay, privilege of personal soul-saving work for the Master. Rosa's
               quest has brought me face to face with the insignificance of this world, and the
               realities of the next. Her attitude is only what that of every true follower of God
               should be. Our citizenship is in heaven; from whence also we look for the Saviour,
               the Lord Jesus Christ. If we could only remember our position in Him, the surrendered
               life would be the natural outcome, and, like Rosa, our faces continually would be
               turned toward the beautiful land. </p>
            <p>"This is only another verification of the fact that a little child shall lead them. </p>
            <p>"Yes, it means a rich and new blessing to me!"</p>
            <p>"And to me, too," softly sobbed Mrs. Gray, "fer it's <d:pagebreak
                  role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="113" />all come through her, the sweet lamb,
               and I've been a-threat'nin' to lick her. She was that patient when my ankle was
               twisted, that I'll never fergit it, no never! I can see now how she'd shake of fear
               when she'd come up to me, then run to poor old father fer a bit of comfort. I didn't
               know it then, but do now, that she was 'most a-starvin' fer the kind of love she
               didn't git. How she must have missed her ma! Oh, I've been so awful mean! I don't see
               how God can fergive me, but I know He has. I never knew'd before that the Saviour is
               fer sech as me. Tom used to try to tell me, and I wouldn't let him. He wuz good, and
               I wuzn't. And dear old father! How happy he and Tom must be tonight, but it'll be
               dreadfully lonesome with them all gone. I wish I could have Rosa back ag'in, though
               I'm awful glad she's to have sech a good home. And I made sech a fuss about a-keepin'
               her till spring. If it hadn't been fer her, I don't know how I'd ever got along when
               I couldn't walk. But God has fergive me now, and I feel like another woman." </p>
            <p>"I'll go back with you, Mis' Gray," faltered Rosa, "if you want me to."</p>
            <p>"No, my child, you promised to stay with me," interrupted the doctor, "but you may
               visit Mrs. Gray every week, and I shall see that she never wants for anything again." </p>
            <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="114" />
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="116" />"Ain't He a wonderful
               Saviour?" said Mrs. Gray, brightening up. "I can't see how 'tis, but I love them all
               over there on Burton street now, and I used to be that ugly they're all afraid of me,
               I know. Seems like I can hardly wait till mornin', I'm that anxious to git back to
               tell them all about it. They're all so poor, and have sech heavy loads. They need Him
               bad to help them, but they don't know He's promised to. And Billy Bruce, the poor
               laddie, I want to tell him how sorry I am fer a-tryin' to throw that piece of coal at
               him. His ma's drunk most of the time, and so's his pa. He used to come to me fer
               somethin' to eat, and I wouldn't give him a thing, but jest scold him and tell him to
               git out of the way, fer I didn't feed beggars. He ain't never had no chance yet, and
               I'm jest a-goin' to see what I can do fer him. He's got a good heart, and once he
               told me I'd never lick Rosa if he wuz only a little bigger. He'll run when he see me
               a-comin', but I'll put some peppermints in my pocket, and mebbe they'd help catch
               him." </p>
            <p>"Oh, Mrs. Gray," said Esther, "I am so glad that you are going to help Billy. I saw
               him the other day, and feel sure that you can bring him around all right. I shall
               come over often to assist you, and I know that many will find the same dear Friend in
               whom you are rejoicing tonight. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="117" />"How wonderfully has the
               Lord's hand been guiding since first I saw Rosa that cold December day; and the end
               is not yet!" </p>
            <p>For several minutes the little company sat in silence, each one buried in thoughts
               too deep and sacred to find expression in words. </p>
            <p>Presently Rosa lifted her head from the doctor's shoulder, her lustrous eyes becoming
               more luminous than ever, as she said: </p>
            <p>"Oh, how glad I am that I have found the way to the beautiful land! Mother's there,
               and don't cough no more. Grandpa's there, and we're all going some day, 'cause Jesus
               paid the fare a long time ago!" </p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <h>AFTERWORD. </h>
            <p>One bitterly cold December day, while riding in a streetcar in a large city, a
               frail-looking little girl, bending beneath the weight of a huge package, entered the
               car, sitting directly in front of me. She was thinly, though neatly, clad. Her pale
               face was overshadowed by an expression of care far too old for her baby shoulders,
               while her eyes were large, dark, and pathetically wistful. </p>
            <p>There was something irresistible about her whole appearance, impelling me to cross
               the aisle and sit down by her side. </p>
            <p>She told me that her name was Rosa, and the conversation which followed, suggested
               the story, " <em>Rosa's Quest</em>." </p>
            <p>I asked her if she knew anything about Jesus. To this she replied:</p>
            <p>"Not much, ma'am, but it seems like I've heard just a little."</p>
            <p>Of heaven and the way of salvation she was as ignorant as a child in the wilds of
               Africa. The sad expression of her face did not alter till I quoted John 3:16, then
               looking up with a smile she said: </p>
            <p>"Ain't that pretty?"</p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="119" />For some time we talked, her
               hungry soul eagerly drinking in the old, old story, but to her so new. </p>
            <p>Suddenly she left the car, and with a sense of deep depression, I saw her disappear
               amid a great, seething mass of humanity. </p>
            <p>If she has not succumbed to the hardships of poverty, she probably is still toiling
               on in that proud "Christian" city, and has any one taught her more of Jesus than she
               knew that day? </p>
            <p>Who will be responsible for these lost souls, constantly coming into contact with
               those who profess to know the Lord? </p>
            <p>Why is it that so many Christians view life from an inverted standpoint, attaching
               apparently vastly more importance to the few brief years spent upon this earth, than
               to the countless cycles of eternity? Why not view it normally, making our one
               business that of serving that blessed Christ? </p>
            <p>Surely the saddest word in a Christian's vocabulary is indifference. By-and-by many a
               one would doubtless gladly forfeit ten thousand years of heavenly bliss just to
               recall the wasted opportunities of this day. </p>
            <p>It is an incomparable privilege to be a child of the King, and the only way in which
               one may prove his appreciation and loyalty is by the degree of consecration and
               quality of service rendered. </p>
            <p>
               <d:pagebreak role="xhtmlvocab:separator" value="120" />At the day of Christ's
               appearing there will be many an unrewarded Christian, saved eternally by the precious
               blood of God's sacrificial Lamb, but with no glittering starry crown to cast at those
               once-pierced and bleeding feet! </p>
            <p>If the reading of this little story draws any nearer to the Lord, influencing them to
               become more diligent in their search for the lost, it shall accomplish that whereunto
               it is prayerfully sent. </p>
            <!-- End of level2-->
         </section>
      </d:bodymatter>
   </d:book>
</html>
